1880年代末起
since the late 1880s
視覺藝術家和說故事的人
visual artist and story-tellers
開始使用動態影像來創造神奇的世界
have used moving images to create amazing worlds
電影給我們啟示
movies have inspired us
激勵我們並捕捉我們的想像
thrilled us and capture our imaginations
膠卷，曾幫助我們分享經驗和夢想
film, has helped us to share our experiences and dreams
化學膠卷曾經是唯一用來
photo chemical film, has been the exclusive format
捕捉、沖洗、放映和儲存動態影像的格式
capture, develop, project and store moving images
百年來不曾變過
for over 100 years
近些年才發展起一種新技術
it was only resently that a new technology had immerged
代表影像品質和工作流程的膠卷，其崇高地位正受到挑戰
that challenging film place of gold standards for quality and workflow
數位技術已經進化到可以替代膠卷
digital technology is evolving to a point that
執行最主要的任務：
means very well replace film as the prirary mean
創造和分享動態影像
of creating and sharing motion pictures
這部記錄作品叫《side by side》
the documentary doing is called side by side
涉及到數位電影的科學、藝術和影響
it's the documentary about science, art and impact of digital cinema
一百年的化學膠卷發展
100 years of photo chemical film making
目前已經到達了一個臨界狀態
right now it reached a kind of threshold of tipping point
這場對話，這個關鍵時刻
in this conversaton, in this intersection of time
是歷史性的
is historic
我們怕是已經來到了
we've kind of come to this place where
膠卷電影的末日
it is the end of film
我們今在何方
where are we today
這很令人興奮，因為這是重新創造的新媒介
it's exciting, because it's a re-invention of new medium
如果化學攝影法可以呈現我們的綺麗文化
if the photo chemical process has virtues through our culture
另一形式有何不可？
why aren't you another level
關鍵是你怎麼用它說故事
how do you use it to tell a story
怎麼用它去描繪一個情境
how do you use it to paint apicture
您打算和膠卷一刀兩斷了嗎？
are you done with film
不要故意引導我，基努
don't hold me to it, Keanu
不過
but…
我想是的
I think I am
數位攝影機是電影業的新美學手法
digital cameras are the new aesthetic that coming to cinema
同時我們又哀悼膠卷的凋零
and at the same time we are going to mourn the loss of film
我可以明確的指出為什麼要用膠卷拍電影
I am costly(?) to justify where and why I shoot a film by film
不過實話說我沒聽說過誰知道為啥一定要用數位拍電影
But I don't hear anybody being honestly to justify why they want to shoot a film digitally
我希望我所想像的一切都能真實展示
I want everything I could imagine to be something we can realize
不過膠卷很難實現這一點
I saw the door opening on a field of possibility that you just couldn't do it with film
如今比較悲哀的是
It's really sad right now
攝影開始大量使用數位技術
to see cameras cording imagery a serial way
取代膠卷
starting to take over film
膠卷拍攝
我不需要把我的油畫換成蠟筆畫（畫面質感）
I'm not gonna trade my oil paintings to seta crayons
數位拍攝
有人看好數位技術
there will be people who will chip in digital
也有人不僅想殺掉這隻生金蛋的鵝
there will be people who will not only kill the goose lay the golden egg
還要在之前把它搞得一團糟
they'll sort of mess it first
如果數位技術取代膠卷
if the intention of that digital will replace film
正好是因為我們所討厭它的一些方面，那很悲哀
I'll be sad if it's doing acturally exactly where we hate it
因為數位能夠做的膠卷效果，膠卷當然做得更好
because that digital now can make it look like film that film is inherently better
若就因為我們喜歡這種更好的感覺
just we like the way it looks better
（就否定數位技術）這有點專斷
which seems kind of arbitrary that we were used to
膠卷是19世紀的發明
film is a 19th century invention
我們已經到達了化學攝影法的頂峰
we are on the top of photo chemical process
很難再有進步
this is about as far as ever we can go
數位技術發展至今
digital is here now
還有很長的路要走
but it's gonna keep going
你會是數位發展的參與者
and you're gonna be part of that
參與者將決定數位技術的未來
who's be gonna be a part of that dictating where that goes
我覺得膠卷不會怎樣
I don't think films going anywhere
我不覺得影像從此將完全摒棄膠卷
I don't think it's to the image or anybody to totally eliminate film
會有很多人加入我們，為膠卷而戰
there gonna be many of us, they'll fight for film
為在感光劑上攝影的經驗而戰
fight for the experience of shooting on emulsion
我們處於某種變革的迷霧中
we really are in the mist of some sort of revolution
這種變革威脅到影片的基本品質
that threatens the status qual
所以這既是可怕的又是輕易
it's so potentially either scary thing or very liberating thing
電影製作第一步：
one of the first steps of production process
捕捉影像
is capturing the images in camera
導演、演員、攝影師和製作團隊
the director, actors, cinematographer and the entire production team
共同努力讓劇本活起來
work together to bring the script to life
攝影技術師，也叫攝影指導或DP
the cinematographer, also called the director of photography or DP
幫助導演達成電影的影像效果
helps the director achieve the look of the movie
DP的職責在於決定攝影裝備
the DP is responsible for knowing what equipment is needed
以及深諳其攝影原理
and how it works in order to capture the scenes
攝影指導要注意色彩和構圖
a director of photography looks at color and composition
大衛 芬奇 導演
（社群網戰 / 鬥陣俱樂部 / 火線追緝令）
以及角度和其他構成電影的元素
and angles and all those things in terms of how the movie is being built
光照到皮膚的感覺，光穿過頭髮的效果
the quality of light of skin, the quality of light through hair,
光透過窗戶反射在地板上的效果
the quality of light through the window and bouncing off the floor
這些都要與真實世界相同
they're equating the building of this world
包括每個物件的
and terms of energy
光學反射效果
that reflects off objects
關鍵在於
the question is about
如何讓構圖跟情感穿越畫面到人的心裡面
framing, sensibility, how to make people feel
邁克爾 查普曼，攝影師
（計程車司機 / 蠻牛 / 粗野少年族）
把情緒付諸光影
bringing emotion into the lights
基於要恰當的處理光影
comes from being appropriate and somehow being
不過更棒的是超越“恰當”
the really great is, more than appropriate
真正讓人驚奇的是
they really startle you with how wonderfully
我能如何漂亮的呈現所有動作
I could have this look is on whatever they're doing
計程車司機，1976
這種專業技術水準上
That level of crossmanship? or technical expertise
約翰 麥德森，攝影師
（神鬼戰士 / 浪人47 / X戰警：第一戰）
你沒法解釋自己要做什麼
You can't explain what you're gonna do
所以他們必須把你當回事
so there is a certain matter of leap of faith that they have to having you
現代啟示錄，1979
維多里歐 史托拉洛，攝影師
（現代啟示錄 / 末代皇帝 / 小活佛）
作為攝影師
To be a cinematographer
要有藝術方面的知識
is to have the knowledge of the art
毫無疑問，電影是一種利用科技實現的綜合藝術
Without any doubt, cinema today is a mix of art in technology
大衛 史坦普，視覺特效
（X戰警，X戰警2，星戰毀滅者）
如今在這個領域還要懂點技術才行
Today, in this area, you also have to be a bit of technician
你得懂設備
You have to know the equipment
明白成像流程的所有環節對DP來說非常重要
It's really important for DP to understand the entire links of the image chain
從完成任務到創新
From acquisition to excavation
攝影機是測量光跡並使其聚焦
The camera is a tool that focuses and measures
並以影像形式將其記錄的工具
Photons of light and record them in images
透過膠卷攝影機
With a film camera
光透過鏡頭並照射到電影膠卷上
Light enter through the lens and hits the frame film behind the lens
膠卷表面塗有含鹵化銀晶體顆粒的乳劑
The film is covered emulsion that contain grains of silver halides crystals
這些晶體在光照下會發生化學反應
These crystals react chemically when light hits them
顯影時晶體會轉化為金屬銀
And the crystal change to silver metal when they are developed
這樣拍攝的影像就在膠卷上形成了
A photograph image is formed on the film
瑞德 穆拉諾，攝影師
（冰原之心 / 我們是一群小鳥 / 親親愛倫）
對於膠卷的質感和顆粒感
There is something about the texture of the grain structure of film
我個人會調整直到覺得舒服
That personally I hold on till it's like a comforting thing to me
這種感覺更像是可觸的
And it feels more tangible
我打開並輕擊它們的時候很有質感
How I open up and flip themselves give sort of touch of quality
布拉德福德 楊，攝影師
（賤民 / Nasceu Maria / 受詛咒的密西西比）
這種圖片的顆粒感
Still have some granularity in the image that
可以讓強光生動
keeps high light living and keeps blacks
並賦予暗光更多微妙特性
with a little bit more nuance characters in them
迪克 普伯，攝影師
（秘密與謊言 / 魔術師 / 無憂無慮）
我熱愛顆粒感和紋理
I greaten grain and texture
它們能給你多種多樣的選擇
they give you a variety of different opportunities
魔術師，2006
膠卷拍攝的基本流程
The workflow on the film set
就是你要帶上幾千呎的膠卷
Basically means that you take thousand-foot load of film
裝到膠卷盒裡
loaded in to the magazines
每卷也就夠你拍個10分鐘多一點
And that enable you to shoot for roughly 10+ minutes per roll of film
接著是休息時間
And it gives a natural break of action
這時候有人把拍滿的膠卷拽出來
when someone pulls the magazine off the camera
再把新膠卷放進去
And put a new magazine on
接著這些膠卷會被送到膠卷實驗室
Then the film goes away to the film lab
過夜顯影
And it developed over night
然後沖印
And printed
第二天樣片出爐
And in the next day, you could see dailys
有好多年這都是一件樂事
There was a joy for many many years
珊迪 希瑟，攝影師
（拜見布朗一家 / 早安孟買 / 餓鬼之家）
因為我們是片場幽靈
For us to be the genes on set
所以我們熱愛樣片
That's why we like dailys
我們都去表演，我們喜歡這樣
We'd all go, we'd act, we'd like
我們愛幹嘛幹嘛，也喜歡我們幹的事
We'd do all we do, and we'd love what we did
接著每個人都入了迷
and then everybody would rapt
然後第二天一早我們回實驗室的時候
and the next morning we came back in the lab
我們驚訝的說：看我們都幹了什麼好事
We went “wow, look what we got.”
這真是神奇
You know it was magic
唐納 麥卡派恩，攝影師
（金剛狼 / 紅磨坊 / 終極戰士團）
攝影指導是魔術師
The director of photography was a magician
他是唯一真正可能知道
He was the only? one who actually, probably knew
第二天樣片會怎麼樣的人
what's gonna beyond the screen the next day
這給了你不少權勢和夥伴
And this gets you a lot of authority and pal
拍攝的時候你得有種堅定的信念
There is a certain believe of faith you take when you shoot the film
這很浪漫的
And there are something really romantic about that
樣片回來每個人都興沖沖想看看你拍了些什麼
Get your dailys back and everyone being really excited to see what you got
我不喜歡被樣片背叛
I don't like the betrayal of dailys
我不喜歡去全神貫注的看表演時候
I don't like going in and seeing and getting swept up with the performance
在25呎的螢幕上發現拍攝失焦了
And then seeing go out focus on 25-foot screen
而且還知道這重來不了
and knowing that there's no way to retrieve that
羅伯特 羅德里格茲，導演/攝影師
（萬惡城市 / 小鬼大間諜 / 英雄不回頭
拍電影的時候有種感覺
But in like a film about that feeling
過了半天一天
midway to the day, end of the day
真的拍了什麼東西嗎？我不記得我拍了些什麼
did we get anything, that day? I didn't remember, I didn't get it
因為你看不見所以沒有拍過的痕跡
Didn't feel we put the flag in it cause you couldn't see
就像關了燈畫畫
it's like painting with the lights off
但是DP會告訴你：
But the DP will tell you:
沒啊，燈沒關，都在我腦子裡呢
it's not, the lights aren't off, it's in my head
在他腦子裡，這不錯
It's in his head, well that's great
但扛攝影機的不是我
but I'm off bringing the camera
選鏡頭的也不是我，我就管表演怎麼樣
picking the lenses, I'm judging the performances
數位攝影機不使用膠卷
A digital camera does not use film
相對的，鏡頭後是電子感光元件或晶片
Instead, it has an electronic sensor or chip behind the lens
感光元件由許多微小的圖像元素構成
The sensor, is made up with millions of tiny picture elements
或簡稱圖元
or pixels for short
當光進入攝影機的時候
when light enters the camera
撞擊元件並產生各自獨立的電子電荷
it hit the pixels and create individual electronic charges
這些電荷被放大後轉化為代表圖像的數位資訊
these charges are magnifying converted into digital data that represent the image
大衛 塔特肖，攝影師
（星際大戰1-3 / 駭速快手 / 綠色奇蹟）
用膠卷拍攝由於它一直在轉
ring the film that it just constantly moving
所以總有點模糊
So the result is kind of fuzziness
而圖元這樣的東西
well the pixel kind
是非常細緻精確的
is very fine-line, accurate, exact thing
用帶顯示器的數位攝影機
with digital cameras in monitors
你能在拍攝的同時觀看拍下的東西
you are able to see exactly what you are recording on sight as you're shooting
不同於膠卷攝影機
unlike film cameras
你不用等上一天才能看自己拍了些什麼
you don't have to wait a day to see what you've captured
樣片不再是“隔天的”
they're no longer dailys
而是“即可得的”
they are “immediatelys”
費爾 麥休克斯
（皇家賭場 / 蒙面俠蘇洛 / 藍色小精靈）
你坐在片場或帳篷什麼的地方
You sit round back of the set or in the tent somewhere
看著巨型顯示器
looking at the huge monitor
然後透過這個作調整
and make adjustment from that
這和現場調整沒什麼兩樣
which is actually quite alike
因為你看到畫面就是現場
because that means you seeing the picture exactly it is
用膠卷的話，一個拍攝
And with old film, a capture
要過夜才能看，而且有時會擔心
it was overnight and sometime you got the burden
我是不是拍的沒問題
that “I wonder if I go there right”
(?)我認為不管樣片有多好都得有個後備措施
(?)I think we need more backine and don't worry how great daily is
喬治 盧卡斯，導演/製片人
（星際大戰1-4  /  500年後  /  美國風情畫）
誰都知道看樣片怎麼回事
They know as well as anybody that you go to dailys
不過我真覺得應該有更多後備措施
and I really think there should be more backline in there
你要是在片場幹過
But If you do it on the set
就知道後備措施的重要性了
You can understand it, more backlines
（數位攝影）實現了這點，這很好，就是我想要的
And they do it, it's ok cause that is exactly what I want
因為在電影院放出來也是這樣
cause it exactly is the way could be in the movie theater
人們都這麼說：
People speak about:
謝天謝地，我能看見我正在拍的東西
thank god, I can see what I'm getting on
我不用等到明天早上了
I don't have to wait until tomorrow
我能更專注，我知道我在拍什麼
I can see it and focus on it I know what I'm getting
克里斯多夫 諾蘭，導演
（黑暗騎士 / 全面啟動I / 記憶拼圖）
在片場看顯示器
few watching the monitor on set
你覺得你真的看到你拍的東西了
and you feel that you really seeing what you've got
其實這種想法欺騙了你
this thinking is fooling yourself
你的觀眾是要在1000倍大的螢幕上看這些東西
Your audience are gonna watch the film on the screen is 1000 times bigger
你只是在大電視上看
you watch it on large TV
沒錯，你能看見自己拍了什麼，就在那
Yes, you see what you get it, that's right there
馬丁 史科西斯，導演
紐約黑幫 / 計程車司機 / 四海好傢伙
我的經驗建議之後再看拍的東西
Proof for me that I think you need to see rushes later
我認為這是集中精力的方法
I think it's concentrate
表演或僅僅是動作
But the performances or just the movement
你可以在特定的時間去看
that is something you can see in a special time
攝製電影的過程是攝影指導的技術和秘密
The process of shooting film was the DP's art and secret
查理 何茲費得，特藝彩色紐約市場部高級副總裁
現在攝影師只是數位攝影前面的顯示器
Today the cinematographer is a monitor on the digital shoot
他們拍什麼都能被看見，並任人評判
and everything they are doing could seen, criticized and questioned
有時這挺讓人分心的
It's very distractive sometimes
喬 舒馬赫，導演
（蝙蝠俠3 / 絕命鈴聲 / 粗野少年族）
我和幾個演員一起工作
I work with a couple of actors
每天堅持和其中某一個看（樣片）
that insist on I'm look at it everyday with one of the actors
我可以邊看邊說
I was able to talk among of it
因為這能讓他的表演變得非常自信
because it's making his performances very self-conscious
是嗎？
Right?
你是不是聽說他們都只看他們的頭髮而已？
Are you also convinced that everybody is just looking at their hair?
作為攝影師最大樂趣之一
One of the great pleasure that being a cameraman was
那些尊崇製片人意願的人
that the people who was the suits on the producer
他們都覺得自己知道怎麼表演
They all think they know how to act
他們都覺得自己知道怎麼寫劇本
they all think they know how to write
他們都覺得自己知道怎麼導演
they all think they know how to direct
但是他們都知道自己不會攝影
But they knew they didn't knew how to shoot
這完全取決於你
So I say this is really got on you
你可以說：看吧，這片子是你做的
you could say: here, this the media you do it
我才是魔術師
I was the charmer
不過現在會攝影是另一碼事了
But now, being a thing that you can shoot is not like it used to be
有些攝影師之所以當攝影師
There're cinematographers who became cinematographers
是因為他們熱愛攝影的魔力
because they love the voodoo of it
他們喜歡導演對他們說：
They love it when the director said to them:
“那個角落
“down that cornor”
你能看見嗎？好像要消失了”
will you able to that? that's kind of melt away”
他們倒是機靈：“明天看嘛，肯定超驚喜，包你滿意”
they get to guile: “ just wait till tomorrow, it's gonna be amazing, you're gonna love it.”
火線追緝令，1995
接下來，我經歷過的，他們把樣片搞定了，我就會…
and then, I had this experience, they've set the dailys then I've gone
比如《火線追緝令》裡有些令人興奮的東西就是表現不出來
some of the durance can't just work on se7en you just go "wow"
不過倒是有個差不多的人在，所以你就會
but there is the an equal man on time so you go:
看著它說：“這他媽怎麼回事？”
look at it and say: “what the fuck?”
現在有了數位攝影機
Now with digital cameras
人人都能看見拍攝的結果
everyone could see exactly what things were going to look like
這改變了你從前對攝影的喜愛方式
that changes the way you like it
甚至改變了你的表演
it may even change your performance
因為這給拍電影帶來了完全不同的感受
Because it creates a different feelings in the whole thing
這讓我們的創造性有了更多空間
It gives us more scope to be creative
這點令人興奮
That was exciting
傑夫 波爾， 攝影師
（街頭霸王：春麗傳 / 變異編年史 / 黑暗鄉村）
對我來說這就是數位攝影機革命的全部
That for me it's digital revolution of cameras all about
貝爾實驗室 出品
1969年，在位於紐澤西的貝爾實驗室
In 1969, at bell labs in New Jersey
喬治史密斯和威樂鮑爾
George Smith and Willard Boyle
提出電荷藕合裝置（CCD）構想
came up with the idea for the charged couple device
兩位老爺子因此獲得2009年諾貝爾物理學獎
並發明了第一個CCD晶片
and the first CCD chip was created
CCD的特點之一是
One of the things that makes the CCD unique
它可以執行某些特殊功能
is its ability to performs specialized functions
例如當攝影機用
such as acting as a camera
你所看到的我們在電視上的圖像
The image that you see on the TV screen aboout of us
就是在我們前方的這個小CCD攝影機拍攝的
is being produced by the small CCD camera which is directly in front of us here
70年代早期，在參觀貝爾實驗室後
In the early 1970s, after a visit to bell labs
索尼公司開始應用CCD技術推廣並發展新產品
SONY started investing in and developing products using the CCD technology
盛田昭夫是索尼之父
Akio Morita was the father of SONY
亞列克 沙匹羅，索尼市場部高級副總裁
他是好萊塢的擁簇
He was always an amor of Hollywood
而設計電子攝影機是他的夢想
And it was his dream to design an electronic camera
能創造和35mm膠卷同等或更佳品質的圖像
That could create images were equaling or better than the 35mm film
廣告：隨時隨地，想拍就拍
record what you want , when you want
80年代中期
In the mid of 1980s
索尼生產了第一批消費型CCD可攜式攝影機
SONY was producing its first consumer quality CCD camcorders
哥本哈根，丹麥
90年代
In the 1990s
小型SD攝影機開始用於數位拍攝
small standard definition cameras began recording digitally
它們開始用於電影拍攝
They were first to use cinematically
始於在丹麥興起的“道格瑪95”運動
when they were embraced by the dogma 95 movement in Denmark
您能不能談談
Can you speak a little bit about
您是什麼時候開始使用數位…
Where did you first coming to digital…
拉斯 馮 提爾，導演
（白痴 / 反基督者 / 黑暗中漫舞）
實際上是偶然
Actually it's by chance
因為我們搞了個“道格瑪95”
Because we made this thing called dogma 95
而且制定了一些規則
And we made up some rules
其中一條是
And one of them was that
必須使用35mm拍攝
the thing has to be filmed by academy 35mm
接著另一條又說
And on e of them said
必須是手持攝影機
it had to be hand-held camera also
然後我提議，既然如此
And then I said, if that is the case
我們也能用錄影
we can also use video
那時候又正好這些攝影機問世了
And that was just at the same time that these cameras came to appear
安東尼 多德 曼妥是第一個拍攝“道格瑪95”的DP
Anthony Dod Mantle was the DP who shot the first dogma film
由湯瑪斯 溫特伯格執導的《家宴》
Thomas Winterberg‘s  celebration
(?)用數位拍攝還能保證電影的純粹性嗎？
(?)Was it pure also of digital video？
攝影機比較輕，這麼點重量不足以…
The lightness of the camera, the weight that you couldn't…
我第一次用這個是這樣的：
I tell you it was the first hit me
我去哥本哈根的農貿市場
I was coming up the food market in Copenhagen
安東尼 多德 曼特，攝影師
（那一個晚上 / 28天毀滅倒數 / 貧民百萬富翁）
我有台索尼PC3，就是我拍《那一個晚上》的那一台
I had a SONY PC 3 and that's the exact camera I end shooting celebration
我記起生機勃勃的擁擠場景
and I remember scenes crowd with lives
假設我們穿過這樣工業化背景的地方
Supported us just moving across this field with a industrial backdrop
有霧，模糊，這種感覺很哥特
Into mist and hazing, it's gothic
我才開始學習怎麼用它
I was just learning how to play with it
到處拍，對這小東西有種怪怪的感覺
Swept it around and I got this weird moment of this midgetcy
又輕又小
Of lightness and midgetcy
而當我看到畫面時又頗感震驚
and I looked at the image and said “my god”
這可以是很好的攝影機
and that's gonna be nice cameras
我認為
I called that
那一個晚上，1998
用微型攝影機拍攝《那一個晚上》有很多話可說
Too much say when I was shooting in celebration on the small cameras
因為我想成為《那一個晚上》的主角
Casuse I want to be a protagonist on celebration
電影的構成實際上就是攝影機充滿情緒化的移動
The combination of the movie is actually emotional movements of the camera
這決定了電影的視角
which probably defined that film's visual line
應該把它與演員的表演
should depart them from the actors
和劇本的指導分離開
and the watching great script
用這台攝影機，這些問題迎刃而解
with that camera and I suddenly solve these smooth
這種移動方式是從前的攝影經驗裡沒有的
it's possible movements I didn't know in my cinema
而這變成了我對《那一個晚上》的貢獻
And that became my donation for  celebration
《那一個晚上》意味著什麼
What  celebration meant
其他這個領域的電影又意味著什麼
and what a lot of the other films at that area meant?
白癡，1998
是不是要完全重新思考電影製作的技術層面了呢
Was that you just have to completely rethink the technical side of the film making
敏郎悲歌，1999
這些電影讓人完全可以為了創意而創作
they brought people to film making for creativities sake
驢孩朱麗安，1999
國王不死，2000
這些電影證明電影製作原理只是為創意服務而已
They pointed out that the mechanism of film making only serves creative
查克和貝克，2000
用DV拍攝
With DV
傑森 科略特，製片
（查克和巴克 / 咖啡與香煙 / 索命麻醉）
都是為了…
Came this whole idea of
等等
wait a second
要是我們能降低預算
if we lower our budgets
作為導演和製片人來說就能有更大的自由度
we get more freedom as directors and producers
用DV拍電影意味著這就是一坨屎
Shooting a film on video of that point meant it was crap
喬弗利 吉爾莫，電影節導演
（崔貝卡電影節 / 日舞電影節）
這基本上是個難以接受的事實
It was almost unaccepted truth
你並沒有認真拍電影
that you didn't shoot films
因為那是錄影格式
that you're serious about on any kind of video format
我們去那然後說：
We just started going out there and we are saying:
聽著，我們要用數位拍攝
Look, we're gonna make movie digitally
我們要做導演最終剪輯
we're gonna give director's final cut
全程盡在掌握
Totally create of control
不過我們會讓這一切更省錢
But we'll make them cheaper
我們的第一部電影是《查克和巴克》
And our very first movie was chuck and buck
你好啊貝克
Hey Buck
…好呀
uh, Hi
喝點啥嗎？
can I get you something to drink?
不用，沒事
oh, no, that's alright
看重播會嚇到自己
Looking at rushes it will scary yourself
冰糕要嗎？
would you like some icecream?
真的嗎，我愛冰糕耶
really? uh, I like icecream
天哪，看起來真夠業餘
Oh god, it looks so amateur
很多人其實…
A lot of people actually…
都是模仿
come it on hell modeled it looked
你特嗎想什麼呢
what you're thinking you fucking doing, man
我記得我們把它在日舞上放映的情形
I remember when we presenting it on Sundance
可嚇死他們了
they were scared to death
觀影指南上寫的就是這是拿DV拍的
The direction would be “this was shot on video”
這樣的數位元攝製作品作為
The digital presentation did not look nearly
膠卷的替代品簡直難以接受
at any way gonna be acceptable substitute of what film was
因為...色情片
Because of…porn
還有紀錄片
And because of documentary
還有新聞報導
and because of news footage
小型攝影機影片讓你覺得：
Video occupied the space in your mind like:
我在這，在這房間裡，天，一切真的在發生
I'm here I'm in that room oh my god, this is really happening
而這讓《查克和巴克》更好
And that makes chuck and buck better
艾倫 庫拉斯，攝影師
（迷途人生 / 王牌冤家 / 一世狂野）
人們開始
People were starting to think
用完全不同的眼光去審視
in a completely different way about
技術和媒介
How could the technology and medium
如何幫助我們重新思考電影製作
help us to rethink film making
你發現人們開始挑戰傳統觀念
You start to see people start to challenge the idea
迷途人生，2002
像InDigEnt（獨立數位娛樂）這樣的組織
as the group as InDigEnt (Independent Digital Entertainment )
他們製作SD影片
They were creating standard def video
然後用影片拼成電影再放出
That within they converted to film for seen actual released
蓋瑞 文尼克，InDigEnt創始人（已故）
作為一個獨立電影人
I think as a independent film maker
我認為我們正處於最令人興奮的時代
we are at the most exciting time ever
因為現在我們能出去用DV拍攝電影
Because now we can go out and make a film on DV
蝌蚪，2002
奧斯卡交了新女友
Oscar has a new girlfriend
真的嗎
really?
我們昨天好像討論了很長時間這個話題了
it seems last day we get quite late for that conversation
有種想法是你要是用數位拍那就一定便宜
The idea was that if you shoot digitally it was cheap
所以徹底的幫助提升了電影製作的數量
And absolutely helped fill the number of movies that gotten make
我記得我在日舞的頭一年
I remember my first year on Sundance
在虛構作品類中我們遣返了35部提交作品
we return 35 submissions total of the fiction category
幾年以後就翻了10倍
few years later it was 10 times of that
在聖誕斯電影節上
back to that Sundance days
有InDigEnt的作品，人們都覺得還好，畢竟是獨立作品
the releases of InDigEnt, people were saying that's ok for you as independent
卡羅林 卡普蘭，製片
（誘惑我小媽 / 迷途人生 / 非關女孩）
不過這不是電影
But this isn't cinema this isn't…
這種說法很流行，用DV做電影再去日舞
That was a huge saying to make film on a video camera and go to Sundance
我們因《迷途人生》贏得了最佳導演和最佳影片
And win best director, and win beat film for personal velocity
蓋瑞自己的《蝌蚪》
Gary's own film tadpole
就比較傾向於大眾
And being sort of for normal man's money
每個人都在努力：娛樂大眾好賺錢
Everyone worked on it: make money from that sale
這就是大家都覺得用數位攝影沒問題的時候
And that's when a lot of the idea you can shoot film digitally
就像是對商品美學的品頭論足
And it's almost like a production aesthetic
爭論開始了
And that's when all those debates started
您一定知道
You must have heard that late 90s
90年代末電影的金標準和您使用的工具是什麼呢
film's gold standard and the tool you playing with are what?
貶低或推崇
debasing, fattening
我曾經受過打擊…
I have been slapped around if you wanna…
“打擊”是怎麼回事
What do you mean “slapped around”？
(?)我被說成是個爆發同性戀
(?)I mean I've been exploded and homosexualcated for the sentence
對我來說轉投數位攝影是顯然的
It was a quite obvious to me to go to digital
因為你可以熟練使用攝影機
because of mature you can have the camera
這種成熟程度顯而易見
The amount of the mature you can have your camera was obvious
既然我決定用另一種工作方式創作
since I was trying to create another way of working with other tools
這點是比較重要的
And that was essential
大衛 林區，導演
（藍絲絨 / 象人 / 穆赫蘭大道）
為了拍長鏡頭
I imagine there was collaboration for you than
我猜您需要和演員密切合作是嗎
terms of the relationship with your actors for longer takes？
是啊，基努
Yes you know, Keanu
10分鐘到頭了，其實根本沒10分鐘
10-minute is maximum, it wasn't really 10
9分鐘吧也就
9 or something
當那玩意開始轉的時候
When that thing starts rolling
有種感覺
There's kina underline feeling
寶貝開始轉了
that precious stuff rolling through there
這讓所有東西都緊張
And it puts kind of a tension on things
我想拍多長拍多長
Like a shoot as much as I wanted
我可以有最好的表演
I can get the best performances
我不用擔心拍片是燒膠卷
I didn't have to worry about shooting is a little burst of film
這太荒謬了，不過我曾經就是這麼擔心的
That was ridiculous but that was what I had to do
相對來說曾經就是那麼貴
that's how expensive it was comparatively
數位攝影的話，一個小東西能拍40分鐘
Digital, a little gizmo, 40 minutes
你能邊拍
And you can be running this camera
邊和演員講話
and talking to the actor
再來也沒問題
Starting over again
他們能夠融入進去
And they get down in there
能抓拍以前的巨型設備
And catch a thing never would get caught
幾乎從來沒拍到過的東西
if you have the giant thing there
達尼爾 馬丁，導演
（藍調傳奇 / 拉丁情事 / Prison Song)
我喜歡用攝影機工作
I love to on the camera
尤其是到感情洋溢的地方，魔法就發生了
Especially when we were at the emotional place that magic is happening
你喊停的時候，突然間所有人都去那了
When you go cut, That all of a sudden everybody's in there
而你就在那
And you were at a place where it is just there
接著萬物靜止
And then everything stops
接著是“好了，我們繼續”
then “that's ok, now go back to that”
而我說：“等等，要搞下攝影機，一分鐘就好”
And I said “no, just went to the camera, back to one”
你要能夠快歸位
As fast as you can get back to your position
約翰 馬可維奇，演員
（危險關係 / 太陽帝國 / 超危險特工）
你還能再次離開
You can go again
我就是覺得等待的時間好多啊
I just thought there was way too much waiting
電影於我總有個動力問題
Because movies for me there is always momentum problem
因為我成長於劇院，那也是我接受表演訓練的地方
Cause I grow up in the theater and that's how I was trained
不過在拍電影的大多數時間我…
and a lot of time in movies I…
總有種感覺：“我們能走了嗎？”
feel like “can we go？”
對我來說連拍45分鐘簡直太難了
it‘s very tough for me to be able to shoot 45 minutes
不是攝影機換膠卷的問題
Not reload of the cameras
因為整個團隊都不能再集中精神
Because it's true this entire group can't get on concentrate
演員就能集中那麼久，所以你需要2-3分鐘的休息
The actors can only concentrate for so long and you need 2-min-break, 3-min-break
正好換膠卷
during which time you reload
當你用膠卷攝影機拍攝的時候
When you're running a film camera on sight
每個人都比較嚴肅
everyone seems to take things a little bit more seriously
當他們聽見膠卷轉的時候
When they hear the film running
其實基本上聽見的都是錢的聲音
they hear the money running on the camera basically
每個人都全神貫注
Everybody brings an aim
我頭次聽說攝影機裡有膠卷在轉的時候
The first time I'd ever heard the word a film going through a camera
格蕾塔 葛韋格，演員
（愛上草食男 / 阿舍正傳 / 飯飯之交）
又興奮又緊張
It was thrilling also make me very nervous because
因為突然間每一幀都要算錢，而我以前從未經歷過
All of a sudden each take counted in a way that I never really experienced before
在你喊“開始”的瞬間感覺如何
what about that moment after you say “action”
比如對我來說，攝影機開始工作
Like for me, when that cameras rolling
我猜肯定是和錢有聯繫，不過
I guess maybe it's connected to the money but...
10分鐘也太有限了
the 10-minute reel is so finite
這簡直就像競技體育，你得集中再集中..
It's almost athletic thing like focus, focus…
理查 林克萊特，導演
（心機掃描 / 都市浪人 / 年少輕狂）
然後，“嗯這個不錯”這樣
Like that's good for them
其實就是個氣氛
that's just atmosphere though
我的意思是，你要是那麼想肯定感覺的到
I mean if you want that you can create that, right
丹尼 鮑爾，導演
（海灘 / 28天毀滅倒數 / 貧民百萬富翁）
我覺得演員的情況會不一樣
I thought it could make a difference through actors
不用給一堆第二次拍攝機會
Don't give a dozen particularly twice
我可以不斷的調整到他們覺得合適
I Just infinitely give adjust whatever way they have to tell it they'll tell it
你不會暫停也不說：“嘿，能停了嗎”
You didn't ask for a break you didn't say:”hey, can we stop”
你現在用的是數位攝影嗎？--沒錯
You are on digital now -- yeah
我第一次經歷到沒有暫停的拍攝是
Though my first experience is, without which is, there is no cut
和理查 林克萊特合作的《心機掃描》
I worked with Richard Linklater on the film called Scanner Darkly
就像--你繼續吧
It just lik -- you can just go on
對，我哀求道“我們停下來吧”
Yeah, I just like “can we please stop”
停下吧~
Stop~
不，沒那必要
No, we don't have to
但是我想停下來啊！
But I want to！
羅伯特唐尼找到我說：
Robert Downey actually came up to me, and he said:
“這樣工作我不行的
“I can't work like this,
“我找不到我的拖車，我從來也沒整理過自己的東西
“I never get to my trailer, I never get my shit together
“我一天站14個小時，我一直在拍啊拍啊。”
“I'm on my feet 14 hours a day, I'm shooting all the time.”
他把盛尿的石頭罐子放片場了
He actually left mason jars of urine on the set
就放角落裡
Just like over in the corner stuff
他會出去尿完了再放回來
just he will go off and pee in it and bring it back
拿這個跟我抗議
this is like a form of protest
以前，用賽璐珞拍片真的好興奮啊
Previously, what's on celluloid only really has been thrilled
那種獲得賽璐珞聖杯的感覺，很神奇
to arrive a holy grail of celluloid, it's amazing
所以我們的頭幾部電影是用賽璐珞拍的
so we made the first few films on celluloid
而且我做了道不錯的好萊塢大餐
and I made a very big of Hollywood film
《海灘》
the beach
海灘，2000
和李奧納多狄卡皮歐，還有很大的一個工作團隊
with Leonardo Di Caprio, and a big crew
不過這一點也不適合我
and it didn't suit me at all
感覺擔子實在太重
I felt it was too much weight for me really somehow
接下來我看到了《那一個晚上》
And so I then saw celebration
那一個晚上，1998
不像電影，也不像眼見
wasn't so much the film, wasn't even a look
單純的攝影機操作
It was the camera operating
和攝影移動
Movement of the camera
所以我找到拍攝它的人：安東尼 多德 曼特
So I got with the guy who shot it, Anthony Dod Mantle
我覺得像是離經叛道
And I said I feel like not doing the right thing any more
“我們一起做點什麼吧，用數位攝影”
“Can we do something together, Digitally”
我都不知道自己在說啥，不過覺得像個新世界
which I didn't know what I ‘m saying by saying that It was kind like a new world anyway
接著我們就著手製作《28天毀滅倒數》
Then we came with the script 28 days later
28天毀滅倒數，2002
這是我們用消費型攝影機拍的
And we shot it on consumer cameras
但是我記得安東尼對我說過
But I remember Anthony saying to me
這個格式沒問題的，不過我們這輩子也沒法得奧斯卡了
It's all vey well working in this format and he said we'll never get an Oscar
開始的時候有個場景，斯里安墨菲要演的
There was a scene in the beginning what the character Cillian Murphy wanted it run
荒廢的倫敦
A deserted London
要是用膠卷，這片子怕是無法完成
We will not be able to achieve the film on film
因為我們沒那麼多錢去阻斷交通
Because we have to stop the traffic and we did not get enough money to do it
所以我們只是短暫的管制了一下交通
So what we do is just hold the traffic briefly
但是因為我們是用這些攝影機拍的，能用10個一起拍
But because we run these cameras, we could use ten of them
因為太便宜了
cause it's so cheap
而且他可以走過倫敦中心和其他區域
and he can walk through central London and areas of it
我們有10台攝影機，只要交通停止幾分鐘就行
We have 10 cameras of that, so you only have to stop the traffic for a few minutes
接著就有10個拍攝畫面了
Then you would actually have 10 shots
這可是一大進步
That was enormous advantage
我們拿攝影機到處轉
We plays cameras around
不是隨機的、壞的、漫無目的的
Not coinciding not badly not loosely
我試圖控制每個角度而且我知道哪些更好
I tried to control every angle and I know what few ways is best
用哪個更好
What's gonna be used
不過之前可以任意看，來獲得新的設想
But that said you can let anyone there, and have a little new guesses there
你是在拍有很小人像的廣角鏡頭
You are in a wide shot with small figures in it
也就2-3個圖元
They were just like 2-3 pixels
我是說那幾乎啥也沒有，就是顏色而已
I mean there's nothing there, they were just color
顏色是比較明智的做法，要是同質拷貝到膠卷上
color is wise if you put it up against exact copy of they were on film
那這張膠卷會巨大無比
The film will be imagerily superior
不過你卻可以偷著拍，代替性的拍，不讓人知道
But you can shoot illegally, substitutedly without people knowing
你可以不照套路出牌
You could do unconventional things
這時影片的節奏
And the rhythm of film which is passed on since it began
(?)鏡頭的連續
(?)Cruise of lens
就都被打斷了,我喜歡這種自由感
You interrupted that, I love that freedom
所以嘗到甜頭後，我知道這樣的設計要怎麼做了
And I got taste for it then, I knew which way to chalk that sequence
所以我正在做這件事，而結果也和我想要的一樣
so I was gonna work on it now, that wasI want it to work
這讓剪輯的工作變得特別（繁雜），因為常常有大量的資料湧入
It makes the editor's job extraordinary cause it's often plumbing through Masses and masses and
masses material
70-80年代
In the 1970s and 80s
電氣公司開始著手可以取代膠卷剪輯的解決方案
electronics companies began working on solutions to replace film editing
100多年來，剪輯人員都是手動剪切粘貼膠卷的
For over 100 years, editing man physically cutting and connecting pieces of film
我們以前常去剪輯室
we used to go to the editing room
他們把膠卷抽到剪切盒裡
they were rolling them into the trim basket
把現在的膠卷放到滾動軸上
they took the film now, and put that through the moving roll
湯姆 羅斯曼，福克斯影業首席CEO
然後像這樣啪啪的把他們粘到一起
and you slap it together like this
那些戴白手套的幹這個難以置信的快
you remember the white gloves and they're incredibly fast at it
我摸到（膠卷）邊緣，有時候很鋒利，會把手指割出血
I find a frame and Sometimes blazing and get your fingertips bloodied
這可是真的“電影上的血”啊
that's just really the blood in the film
我是說真的血，不過現在這一切都變成神奇小按鈕了
So I mean really had it and now it's fascinating buttons
這是一張大家都熟悉的軟碟...
now this is the floppy disk we all familiar…
早期的剪輯系統使用可塑磁碟
early editing systems use moldable magnetic disks
磁帶機和雷射光碟
tape machines and laser disks
來儲存並讀取數位化的膠卷
to store and read digitaled of film
這些系統大多特別貴
most of the systems are enormously very costly
費爾 曼休斯，攝影師
（皇家賭場 / 蒙面俠蘇洛 / 將計就計）
我想後來改變一切的第一件事應該是我知道了剪輯機器
the first thing I have read that changed everything I think it was the digital editing machine
可以花一天把膠卷變成影帶
which spend a daily set and converted film into tape
所以一切從這開始
so that's started the whole thing going
我們研發了一台全數位化的圖像剪輯系統
we start a picture editing system that was all digital
“editdroid”剪輯系統
我們的第一台editdroid在1980年開始工作
we had the first “editdroid” working in 1980
我們最後把它賣給了AVID
and we eventually sold the system to AVID
80年代末
by the late 1980s
AVID把數位剪輯發展成了密集型、有償高效、全電腦控制的系統
AVID had developed digital editing into a compacted cost-effective computer-based system
我第一次看到AVID的時候
when I first saw the AVID
葛列格 伍德，剪輯
（神鬼奇航 / 浪人47 / 午夜凶鈴）
我看見又小又灰暗的圖像在裡面
I have a dimmer image quality was block in, tiny
然後我說，這個要是在五年時間內能把圖像品質提高就好了
and I said: this is gonna be really good if they give the image quality right about in 5 years time
沃特 默奇，剪輯
（現代啟示錄 / 英倫情人 /冷山）
為什麼不試試AVID
why not try it on the AVID
我也是最早那批採用者之一
I'm also one of the earlier adopter people
我喜歡探索未知世界
I like to leap into the unknown
我記得做《英倫情人》的時候
I remember on the English patient
我看著它的畫面說：“天啊，我要怎麼做啊”
I look at in the images and “no, how I'm gonna to be able to do this?”
德里克 安布羅西，剪輯
（超急快遞）
我和老一輩的剪輯一起工作時
when I work with elder editors
他們總是提起電腦剛剛被被用到這項工作上的時候
they'll often to talk about the time when computers were starting to come in
他們對此比較抵觸，因為他們不熟悉電腦
and they were very resistant to it because they weren't familiar with computers
他們害怕因為對電腦瞭解不夠
they were just scared that they didn't know enough about it
可能導致不小心按錯鍵或是意外關機開機，然後啥都沒了
if you push that button or if you accidentally turn it off wrong or turn it on wrong that everything will
be gone
但你要是拿手去做這些情況不可能發生
while that could never happen if you actually physically have the film in your hand
他們覺得自己根本就沒在剪輯，剪輯其實是…
they thought that was not editing, editing is…
不管膠卷怎麼剪輯
so when you're editing the movie on film
都是技術而已，而藝術
that's just technology, the art form
是透過畫面來說故事
is the manipulation of images to tell a story
安 科茲，剪輯
（阿拉伯的勞倫斯 / 永不妥協 / 黃金羅盤）
操作起來挺難的
it was extremely difficult major that
因為我以前沒用過電腦
because I haven't used a computer
我見過老鼠（滑鼠）到處跑，不過可不是在剪輯室
I've seen a mouse somewhere across the floor but not in the editing room
不過我學了，還用了很長一段時間
but I learnt and I keep the machine quite a bit
不過不用電腦我也無所謂，我也喜歡這樣
but once I don't doing on it that's ok and I like it
剪輯處沒有膠卷
there's no film in the editing bay
一切都
it's all…
克里斯 萊本森
（愛麗絲夢遊仙境 / 世界末日 / 捍衛戰士）
一切都好安靜
it's quite
我聽不見以前常聽見的“rururu”的聲音
I don't hear I used to hear the “rururu…”
就是工作臺上的卷軸發出的
the reel on the benches
一直都是非常吵雜的工作環境
it was very noisy kind of buzzing atmosphere
不過現在特別安靜，好像所有的聲音都能像蠟燭一樣被燒掉
and now it's very quite, almost like that you can burn any sound like candles
數位技術把事情變得高效
digital bring you the speed and almost
不過同時也在挑戰你：“我能想那麼快嗎？”
challenge you the sense of “can I think that fast”
“我有時間喘氣嗎”
“do I need time to breathe?”
有時年輕的剪輯總是充滿興趣，還做著非常有趣的工作
sometime are young editors are over-interesting and doing extremely interesting work
但他們不總是有時間安靜坐下來並思考自己到底在做什麼
but they don't always have the time to sit back and think about what they are doing
不過我想他們要是用膠卷來工作
and I think if they work on film
就必須要訓練他們的思想來實現這點
they probably have to train their mind to do that
真的是另一種思考方式
so it's a different way of thinking, really
膠卷用條條框框折磨你
film torture you with discipline
持攝影機的人，1929
用電腦的話就沒那麼痛苦了
that it's gone a little bit from the computer
因為一旦你動了剪子
because you once put the scissors in
就得拿膠布再粘起來
you've been got to join it back with sticky tape
再連到機器上
and bond it through the machine
這個過程你是關鍵
you're much more decisive about that
剪輯過程變更好了嗎？
has editing got any better?
就因為選擇變多了？我覺得不一定
because it's infinite the choice? I'm not so sure
洛倫佐 狄波納文圖拉，製片
（變形金剛 / 特務間諜 /  驚天換日）
不過有件事情比較肯定，現在的很多電影更爛了
but I'm pretty sure that a lot of movies are getting worse
因為你將它推向死亡
because you manipulate it to death
我們會失去很多東西
we may lost something
《阿拉伯的勞倫斯》中，當他劃亮火柴
the cutting that Lawrence of Arabia when he blows the match up
看得出來您有著有趣的幽默感
this is recognized that you have a funny sense of fun
這只是寫在劇本裡
that was the solving script
不過要是有我們今天的數位技術
and if you've been on digital as we have on that today
看准就行了
you just have to see it
不過那時候，電影都是一段一段粘起來的
in those days, the film were bonded together like that
就靠剪輯
just with the direct cut
所以當我們看到這個，我們都驚呼不可思議
so when we saw it, we got “wow, that's fantastic”
想想吧，當時那種感情
just work it, just imagine it, when you feel that feeling
作為影像和聲音的承載體，數位擁有不可思議的可塑性
digital is unbelievably malleable plastic of imatery and sound
這很有吸引力，因為我們要的就是可塑性
and that's seductive, because that's all we do
我們是圖像和聲音的雕塑者
we are sculptors of images and sound
不是說膠卷就做不了
it's not that you can't do it in film
就是操作麻煩，而且想做好很難
it's just harder to do that and make it look good
在數位技術不斷發展的同時
as digital technology continued to grow
電腦生成圖像，及通常說的CGI
computer generated images or CGI
越來越多的出現在電影中
were appearing more and more in movies
大都會，1927
視覺特效，或VFX
visul FX or VFX (Visual Special Effects)
自電影成長初期起就成為了電影製作的一部分
have been part of film making since the earliest years
35:11
伊阿宋與金羊毛，1963
攝影技巧，燈光技術，精細模型和實驗室操作
camera tricks, lighting techniques, elaborate models and lab processes
第三類接觸，1977
都被用作改變真實並提高電影體驗
have all been used to alter realty and enhance the movie going experience
奪寶奇兵：法櫃奇兵，1981
星際迷航2，1982
好多電影都不是想拍就拍的
on many films that the number is unpredicted you can't go out and shoot
所以那些你想要的畫面就只能想辦法製作
so the images you need to see you need to be manufactory in somewhere
約翰 科諾，工業光魔視覺特效總監
（阿凡達 / 神鬼奇航 / 星際大戰1-3）
帝國反擊戰，1980
作為視覺特效總監你得明白
things of visual FX supervisor called on you to understand
提姆 韋伯，FrameStone 視覺特效總監
（阿凡達 / 黑暗騎士 / 人類之子）
你得瞭解到這個世界的時時刻刻方方面面
a huge variety of different aspect of the world around us at any one time
你還得明白光反射不同表面的物理知識
you also understand the physics of the way that light reacts of different surfaces
獨立日，1996
你得明白動畫繪製，人怎麼動，其他的東西怎麼做
you got to understand animation, you got understand the way people move creatures move
你得同時成為藝術家和技師
you have to be an artist and a technician at the same time
這是個奇妙的組合
that's an interesting combination
鄧尼斯 莫倫，工業光魔視覺特效總監
（星際大戰 / E.T. / 侏羅紀公園）
最初的視覺特效師和頭一百年特效師幹的沒什麼兩樣
originally visual FX was done was the first hundred years of the FX was done
用模型和膠卷攝影，能做的實際很有限
they were done with models and with film cameras and they are very limit what you can do
我們花費了很多時間、經歷和人們的努力來做《星際大戰》
but a lot of time and energy and people worked a lot to being able to make star wars film
22年前我入行的時候
when I first doing this about 22 years ago
我學習的環境是真實的，有個舞臺
the environment I learned it was a physical one, it was a stage
亞當 瓦爾德斯，MPC視覺特效總監
（魔戒/ 納尼亞傳奇 /  星艦戰將）
微縮模型、燈光和其他的一些東西都在那
miniatures, camera lights and everything in it
做真實模型有個好處
the great thing about making real stuff is
你要用上全部感情和身體感知
you got to use all of your senses and your physical perceptions and
接著3個人和其他挑剔的模型師站過去
stand there are 3 different people and critical modelers
討論著某件東西在真實光源中是有多酷，那感覺真滿足
talks about how cool something looks like in real lighting is pretty satisfying
拍出來的東西送去用光學印片機
and all those photography was on the optical printer in the end
就是一部大機器，把多層膠卷壓在一起
that's a large device that actually compress layers of film together
然後用這些組合膠卷曝光
and creates new exposures of the film so you can combine it the layers
這樣組合出來的圖像就是電影的最終效果
with images into the final one that you've seen in the movie
視覺特效部，就是實打實的把膠卷一張又一張再一張的疊起來
the visual FX department was literately sandwiching one piece of film next to another piece of film
next to another piece of film
喬納森 福克納，FrameStone視覺特效總監
（阿凡達 / 福爾摩斯 / V怪客）
而這個過程可能引入巨大的人為破壞
and that really introduces huge mantle depredation
1978年，我們剛剛完成了《星際大戰》
in 1978, we had just finished star wars
那時候我們沒找到更好的數位方法，所以製作還是比較艱苦的
we don't find digital sharps in there which were very very cruel
比如那個場景的數學圖像和其他的一些東西
the diagram with that part kind of thing
不過我知道有些人正在用數位技術做電影
but I knew a lot of guys, they were working with the digital film
所以我成立了一個電腦部門
so I start a computer division
我們在那給工業光魔創立了皮克斯
we developed the pixar computer for ILM
我現在就在我們工業光魔3個電腦室之一
I'm right now with one of our three computer rooms we have here in ILM
我們在這有
and what we have here are
時時刻刻都在運作的千千萬萬的電腦程式
thousand and millions of cycles of computer power going by every single second
我有點強迫他們盡可能取工業光魔的資源
so I kind push the staff use as much as they could in ILM
在視覺組能夠提供的情況下
with this graphics crew that we have
星際迷航2， 1982
令人興奮的是
the exciting about it was
（數位製作）沒那麼多規矩
they didn't feel like with a lot of rules
一點也不像“狂野西部”
they really don't seems like kind of wild west
掃描膠卷到電腦上並在那做修改成為可能
it starts to become possible to scanning film and bringing the film into the computer and make
changes to that
數位化膠卷的好處太多了
massive advantage to digitizing your film
可以不必造成任何破壞
with that you couldn't get any depredation
一旦數位化，就是一堆0和1
once it's digital there is 1s and 0s
這些0和1在整個過程中都不會改變
they just stay 1s and 0s all the way down the pipe
數位技術對特效來說變得非常重要
(?)digital became important for a FX point of view
特效舞台中的第一條通道
the first path through the system was in the FX arena
利用數位技術來讓幻想成真
it was using digital technology to realize visions
要是能把膠卷轉換成數位
if you can take piece of film you can turn it into numbers
你能夠控制這些數位再變回影片
you can manipulate those numbers through back to the film
不過卻沒有任何限制
but there's no limit to what you could do
整個世界的大門由此打開
the entire world is wide open
我們所製作的第一個完全數位化的畫面
the first real image that we did that was completely digital
是在《少年福爾摩斯》中
was in young Sherlock Holmes
少年福爾摩斯，1985
我們有個彩色玻璃做的角色
we have a character made of stained glass
那個玻璃看起來像真的
the glass actually looks real
不像畫出來的
not like a graphic in that sort
花了6個月和7場拍攝，很複雜
and it took 6 months and 7 shots which was pretty complicated
不過最後效果出來的時候很不錯
but it's amazing we got it done at that time
詹姆斯 科麥隆，導演/製片
（阿凡達 / 鐵達尼號 / 魔鬼終結者）
喬治總是在數位技術上更進一步
George was always progressive about digital
而且技術平臺的交互性讓人覺得很舒服，很早以前就是如此
(?)and something about the fetch communer you just got comfortable with it really early on
無底洞，1989
魔鬼終結者2，1991
侏羅紀公園，1993
我不笨，我有話要說，1995
我現在要當一隻羊
I was just trying to be a sheep now
哼，狼已經來了
huh, that wolf's in the world already
第五元素，1997
星艦戰將，1997
那時我們還是用膠卷攝影機
now we are still shooting on film
還不能直接使用數位拍攝
we ain't able to shoot on digital cameras yet
鐵達尼號，1997
不過所有的後期製作已經提前數位化了
but all of the post processes is start in front of line
你怎麼進到電腦裡的
how did you going into the computer?
我拿出手來讓他們照張相
I would have my hand and then they would take a picture of it
駭客任務，1999
然後會有台電腦
and then there was a computer
把所有都處理成銀一樣，那就是我的手
it would do the animation of all look silver and silver hand
然後他們就把這個放到大螢幕上給你看
and they will show you on the movie screen
我們在《駭客任務三部曲》的經驗是
our experience on the trilogy
拉娜/安迪 沃卓斯基，導演/製片
（駭客任務三部曲 / 駭速快手 / 雲圖）
當你意識到這點其實很有趣
what was really interesting with that you realize
你其實是在碰運氣
you are really creating these images in toss
你拍不到這些而只能在電腦上做
you couldn't shoot the image you made the image in the computer
90年代中後期
middle to late 90s
(?)您是如何開始進行視覺特效的？
I guess its standard death… visual FX… where do you get in
我們在工業光魔有個做特效的項目
we have program in ILM doing our FX
我們要把膠卷轉換為數位才能完成
we have convert from film to digital in order to do it
這得花一大筆錢，現在我們已經不用再進行這樣的轉換了
it's a huge amount of money just now we don't have to convert any more
膠卷很難處理
film is cumbersome
我想省錢省時間，我要解決這個問題
so I just want to take my money and my time, I'm gonna fix it
我們去索尼公司和他們說
when we went to SONY, and we said:
我們幫你造個數位攝影機吧
we would like to help you work with you to build a digital camera
他（盧卡斯）決定星戰（前傳）第二部要用數位技術拍
he was on the determine that star wars episode 2 can kind be shot digitally
這就意味所有的工作都要為
that means get all that work out, get pipeline figured out for doing
數位拍攝電影準備好
our production at digital cameras
早期數位攝影的問題之一是
one of the problems with early digital capture
圖像的解析度
was resolution
解析度是由很多因素決定的
resolution is depended on many factors
不過最基本的因素是
but in the most basic terms
攝影機所能記錄的圖元數
it is the number of pixels that the camera can record
圖元數越多，解析度越高
the more pixels you had, the higher the resolution
圖像所具有的細節也更多
and more detail a image would have
一部標準SD攝影機
a typical standard definition of resolution of SD camera
通常具有720 × 480的解析度
usually have a resolution of about 720 × 480 pixels
轉折發生在2000年
really, the turn-in point was in the year 2000
我們推出了F900，第一部高解析度攝影機
we came out with F900 camera which was the first high definition camera
在那之前，所有的數位拍攝看起來都像錄影
before that, whatever you look was really look like video
高解析度攝影機可以達到1920解析度，也就是2K以下
high definition cameras record resolution about 1920 pixels across, just under 2K
克隆人進攻，2002
2002年
in 2002
我們完成了《克隆人的進攻》
we did the attack of the clones
這是第一部高解析度攝影的電影
it was the first major feature that was shot high definition
喬治在《星際大戰》中
what George did in star wars movie
實驗性的使用了高解析度攝影機
was take experimental HD camera
其畫面品質已達到膠卷水準
and ply it to feature film parallel
盧卡斯影業，舊金山，加利福尼亞
這在當時是不可想像的
that was unthinkable at that time
不僅僅是對電影協會
it meant that it was around the entire film community
更是對膠卷電影本身
but more deeply mean it was around film itself
那時的好萊塢人們經歷了嚴重兩極分化的時期
it became a really really polarizing time for a lot people in Hollywood
有好多大會都說我是個騙子
we got a lot bit big meetings saying I was doubling carneys
說我會摧毀電影工業和好多人的工作
I was going to destroy our industry, I was going to destroy our jobs
在影院裡他們說：“他嘴上說《克隆人的進攻》是數位拍的，其實不是，
in theater that he said he shot the attack of the clones digitally, but he didn't
“我們聽說他其實還是用膠卷拍的，
we have the words that he actually used film cameras
“他沒用數位拍攝，他欺騙了所有人。”
he's not shooting digital, he's lying to everybody
在1920解析度下，我覺得畫質真的令人震驚
with 1900, I thought the images out there is truly appalling
就是影院品質
I think that was a cinematic camera at all
早些年，我不覺得數位攝影（和膠卷）一樣
in early years, I didn't feel digital capture or digital production was the same
他們總說：看，能看出差別嗎？
they would always say: see, if you can tell the difference?
然後我說能
and I could tell the difference
我們的F900並非為拍攝電影而設計
our first F900 wasn't designed like a film camera
不過喬治盧卡斯用它拍了《星戰前傳》後
of course George Lucas had it shoot star wars
就再也不打算用膠卷拍電影了
like he wouldn't shoot another film on film again
這在好萊塢也獲得了很多支持
and that created quite enough pro in Hollywood
數位技術和數位攝影機
digital technology and digital cameras
看起來像是一種對
looked like a threat to people's existence in
人們思考和工作方式的威脅
way of thinking and way of working
電影製作是藝術
film making is an art
對於傳統的電影製作者來說
to the traditional film maker it looks like
我們像是在糟蹋藝術
we were messing around with art
他們說你為什麼不思進取
and they said why you went backwards, you know what
不過也有很多人說這是有必要的，是前進的必要環節
but it's a lot said about the necessity, a link back be able to spring forward
天行者牧場，加利福尼亞
10年前喬治盧卡斯把大家聚在一起
George Lucas putting up together everybody 10 years ago
在舊金山的天行者牧場開了個會
what a conference he gave the ranch up in San Francisco
澄清了一個事實
and went object of our roles about the idea that
數位技術是不是會把電影攝製終結
digital will put an end to the old cinematography
他說這就是另一個工具而已
he point out that it's just another tool
而且這一點不錯
and that's true
當人們看到了喬治盧卡斯的測試
when people saw George Lucas's test
他們說，這可行不通
they said: that's not gonna work
不過也有人想，我大概會在10年內接受它
it was the same sort of close mind that we're gonna work 10 years to adopt that
我得等等，有人上我就上，我上了大家就都上了
I was gonna wait a little, if someone followed I will be one, I will one and that will be entire
我知道是時候了，總是這樣的
I know the time is it, it always does
《墨西哥往事》片場，2003，設備：SONY F900
我知道這是某件大事的開端
I can tell this is gonna be the beginning of something big
而我想成為這件事的一部分
and I want to be there for that
但是畫面很爛啊
but the image sucked
畫面沒那麼差，就是不如膠卷拍的好
the image wasn't bad, but the image wasn't as good as film
不過卻可以讓我做一些從沒法完成的事
but it allowed me to do something you cannot ever done
萬惡城市，2005
我想到了《萬惡城市》那本書，我知道該怎麼做了
I picked it in my sin city book, and I know how to do it now
我應該用數位拍攝
I got shoot this digital
可以就像漫畫書裡表現的那樣
I can make it looks just like the book
夜晚如地獄般炎熱
the night is hot as hell
樓上有一位女神
upstairs there is a goddess
她說她要我
she's telling me she wants me
如果不是數位攝影，《萬惡城市》不會存在
sin city will not exist if I didn't choose digital film
我甚至根本想不到去拍
I wouldn't even thought to do it
他們想要一些事情推動藝術形式的發展
they wish to do thing that push the art form
技術推動藝術，而藝術也推動技術發展
technology push the art and art push technology
《萬惡城市》的出現石破天驚
sin city came out hit people like break eggs
他們不知道他們看的是什麼
they have no idea what they are looking at
他們想要在表面下的有些東西消失
something hiding from it under rock and hopes it goes away
你完成了一些人認為不可能的事情
you end it up doing something that people didn't realize was possible
效果如此驚人，你知道一切皆有可能
it's so amazed that which it had that knowing anything is possible
這個系統有著你從沒感受過的顏色廣度
the system got better for color and you didn't working of that color space
電影經過了拍攝、剪輯和視覺特效合成後
after the movie is shot, edited and VFX being added
色彩配光師會在實驗室裡繼續調整電影的畫面
the colorist or color timers in the lab make adjustment to the look of the movie
在傳統化學攝影法中
in the traditional photo chemical method
底片要經過顯影和印片
the negative is developed in print is made
在黑白電影時代的配光
timing goes back to the days when there's only black and white
唐 希亞那，特藝彩色配光師
這些畫面展示了舊時實驗室的暗房操作
these scenes showed the dark room operations of the laboratory in the old days
主要就是自己看底片
I had my job it's looked at the negative and the side how long
以及要在顯影床裡泡多長時間
it would have to stay in the beds
第一次如果不行…
if the first wasn't right…
那就繼續泡
dunk, dunk again
所以這就是配光跟時間的關係
so, it was time related
隨著彩色膠卷的發明
with the advent of color film
綠野仙蹤，1939
配光師的工作也變成更具創造性的過程
the timers became more involved into creative process
實驗室裡，色彩配光師、攝影指導和導演決定
at the lab, the color timer, DP, and director determine the look
最後的印片樣式，以在影院上映
for the final prints there will be seen by the public in the theaters
化學攝影中唯一能做的調整是
the only adjustment that can make photo chemically
紅綠藍三原色及亮度的整合
are color bands between red, green, blue and brightness
我們的工作就是達成導演和攝影想要的結果
our job basically is to achieve the vision of the director and the DP
泰瑞 海格，特藝彩色配光師
並在膠卷上實現
and make it happen on a piece of film
我會和導演和攝影坐在一起
like I was sitting with the director and the DP
他們會說這有點太紅或太模糊或太藍了
and they'll say that is a little bit too red, too smear, too blue
然後我們就在頭腦中調整
and we will manipulated in our minds as how much to
怎麼改變或做不同的對比度平衡
change it or to make different cuts balance with each othe
膠卷時代的配光
when the time was on the film
基本上靠腦袋想然後用嘴說
they got to do it pretty much from the head by the tuition
是嗎
yeah
這很難的，非常難
it was hard, very hard
安德列 巴克維亞，攝影師
（非法入侵 / 捍衛戰警 / 魔鬼代言人）
所以為了做到要付出很多勞動和藝術心血
so in order to do this there were a lot of art and labor involved in it
為了達到最後的效果，這些人很努力
these people really work hard to that, achieve that
配光是個很令人沮喪的過程
I still found it very very frustrating that timing process
在片子播放的時候在不停的說，還要跟上剪輯的速度
you kind of talking over the thing while it's running and trying to keep up with the cuts
史蒂文 索德伯格，導演/攝影師
（瞞天過海 / 切 格瓦拉 / 全境擴散）
然後還有些專業辭彙
and saying that I don't know it's a little science to me
他們就不停地把註腳寫下來
something in the guys they are trying to write it down, write the footage down
這個過程一直就是這樣，感覺很瘋狂
as it goes on you can't stop and that seems crazy
數位色彩校正工具首先被使用到短片中
digital color correction tools were first to use for shorter pieces
例如廣告和音樂錄影
such as commercials and music videos
在音樂錄影中配光
basting time in music videos
史蒂芬 索納菲德，DI配光師
（落日殺神 / 300壯士 / 愛麗絲漫遊仙境）
我們完成了最瘋狂的和最具突破性的視覺體驗
and we came up some of the craziest and ground breaking visual images
而來到這樣的一個房間
and it was just amazing ability to come to a room like this
搞一些從來沒人見過的畫面影像
and manipulate something to create images that people never seen before
數位色彩校正開始取代傳統的化學攝影色彩配光
digital color correction began replacing traditional photo chemical methods of color timing
吉爾 柏格丹諾維茲，DI配光師
（胡佛傳 / 經典老爺車 / 心靈傳奇—雷查爾斯的一生）
我的工作就是保證製作人能夠達到他們想要的效果
my job is to be able to make sure the creatives get everything what they want
保證攝影得到他要的對比度
make sure the photographer gets the pilot of contrast that he wants
保證導演想要的電影色調
and the director gets the feelings he wants around movie
保證我們能看到演員的眼睛
make sure that we can see all actors eyes
飽含他想要的感情
and see all the emotion that he wants to see
現在我來建立一個我們說的編輯區
I can now start building what we call power window
在這我可以做任何我想要的改動
in a power window I can change any kind of view I want
比如左邊的這些樹
I just want these trees over on the left
我可以改變它們的顏色
I can take the color that I want on those trees
我能把它隔離出來
and I can isolate it
接著就可以變成任何顏色了
now I can change those trees in any color I want
導演和攝影師會來和我們一起幾周
the cinematographer and the director coming and we spend a couple of weeks
提姆 斯蒂潘，DI配光師
（黑天鵝 / 力挽狂瀾 / 切 格瓦拉）
把電影調整到更好看
grading the film and give it that look make it look beautiful
到他們想要的程度
however they want to look
只要合理我都能做到，這種感覺很棒
I had a great feeling that I can do just about anything you asked me to do it in reason
是誰發明了這個系統呢
who invented this process
你知道曾經用在音樂錄影上的技術吧
the same technology people used for music videos
把畫面變得很酷
create how cool it looks
而現在的技術是過去的10年間發展起來的
and basically what happened was over last 10 years
只是更加進化並自由了
it just evolved and it becomes a lot more free mind
霹靂高手，2000
這是第一部從頭到尾
Over there were art that it was really the first movie
使用特效配光的電影
where at basically that every single frame was the visual fact
為了達到效果用數位技術配光
So its all color times digitally for the look
所以這是第一部DI
So it's a first DI. It's just kind of…
羅傑迪金斯（《霹靂高手》攝影師）在這說：
Roger Deakins sit in the room and saying
我不能用化學攝影法
I can't get what I want in photo chemical
因為每次我想要給配光成美麗的金色藍天就全沒了
Because every time I color time this nice golden color I lose my blue sky
我該怎麼辦啊
what am I gonna do
有點太黃了是不是
it's a little bit yellow isn't it
應該更棕一點
should be sort of more brown
所以我跟他說
So he came in to testing actually I sat with him and showed him
我們能做，我們能做到畫面中的每個細節
Ok we can key it, what we do is we can basically affect everything in the image
不過藍天是不行了，因為這會毀掉其他的東西
except for the blue in the sky also they will ruin overalls
所以藍色就不能用了
so the blue's in wardrobe
不過其他的，像這些綠樹如果不是你要的顏色
but everything else like the green trees that are not in pilot that you want
我們可以把它調成棕黃色
we can exaggerate them in brown gold
所以這部電影的畫面很成功
so out of the successive look for the movie
接著其他的人也跟進
and other people catching on and say
“哇，我也可以試試那個”
woo, I can use that in
接著就變得流行起來
it just became more and more popular
化學攝影配光法真的很令人沮喪
timing is a very frustrating process on photo chemical
很殘酷而且也基本上幹不了什麼
it's very cruelled, hardly to do anything
不過DI就不一樣了
that's a whole thing about DI
我可以圈出一個小東西，可以讓一張臉更紅
while I can go in to circle a little thing and make a face a little bit redder
還可以隔離背景，簡直是天堂啊
and bring out the background I was just in heaven
太不可思議了，我可以做任何事來完成一部電影
it's amazing I can do anything to success movie
現在回想比較有趣的是
what I find interesting now looking back
從我最初成為攝影師的時候開始
to the beginning of experimentation of as a cinematographer like myself
王牌冤家，2004
從電影誕生到數位世界
Going from a film original and the digital world
我們一直在尋找能夠控制畫面並更具操控力的方法
Seeking more control of the image and being able to manipulate the image more
不過現在卻是我們失去了更多控制
And now we actually have lost control
我們放棄了底片，也放棄了成品
Because we then give away our negative, give away our product
能拿到的人都可以對其進行操作
Anybody can take it after that and can manipulate it
這是最後成品很重要的一個方面
(?)this cording is really an important aspect of the final product
我是把電影做成更好的樣子
I'm the one that pushing these buttons to make your film look a certain way
雖然我要接受指示
Yes I'm getting the direction but
不過這需要很多自己的東西來承擔這個責任
it's a lot of my own confidence to crane that certain amount
把它帶領到一個正確的方向
And push that into a certain direction
所以我基本上是真正接觸它的人
So I'm kind of like the last person who really gets the touch of it
攝影師和配光師之間開始變得對抗
It started to become very adversarial between cinematographer and colorist
因為他們都想“他不是決定電影畫面的人，我才是”
because they were like “he shouldn't be determining how the film looks like, I do that”
不過過程之美就在於這是個團隊啊
the beauty of this process is it's a team
這有可能把DP的權利削弱
it could take the power away from the DP but I think it's
不過我認為作為攝影師的工作就是儘量讓拍出來的東西好看
your job as a cinematographer to try your best to see it through the eye
他們會儘量控制DI
They will do everything to make sure they president the DI
來實現他們所想的畫面
And that will supervise that the dare vision they intend was executed
邁克爾 包豪斯，攝影師
（紐約黑幫 / 四海好傢伙 / 神鬼無間）
在《紐約黑幫》裡，他們要我做DI
In gangs of New York  they offer me to do a DI
紐約黑幫，2002
因為每件事都已經準備好了
But because everything was built for us
我們從大螢幕上看見的就是我們想要的
what we had on screen was exactly what we wanted
並不需要DI去改變什麼
It didn't have to have a DI to change everything
我通常都是透過攝影機
but I'm trying always to do it in camera
用光，濾鏡和鏡頭來調整圖像
and with lighting and with filters and lenses
而不是拍完了用DI
But not later in the DI
不過如果你有個特別的故事
OK, if you have a special story
需要你改變現實
when you need to change the reality
那DI就的確是個好東西
Then the DI is something wonderful
因為你可以在畫面上實現你想做的一切
because you can do whatever you want in the image
這很不錯
which can be great, which can be wonderful
一旦電影數位化的拷貝完成了
Once we get done digitally clap cracking your movie
我們會做一份全新的底片去印片
We make a brand new negative and then make a print of that negative
然後我們會對比數位和印片
then we look at the print versus the data in the side by side fashion
把印片和數位匹配
And we dealt in the print to match the data
處理成需要的樣子
To make the print exact the way it should
你對製作母片的工作有什麼感覺
How do you feel about you do all these work to have a pristine
有些印片很完美，有些就（不那麼好）
and you got to have some prints perfect, and some prints…
完成之後你能放得下嗎
Will you let it go once you created it?
說實話去電影院的時候
honestly the truth of the fact is that when you go to a theater
你看到了幾周心血的最終版
You watch that prints used to spend weeks of labor on
其實每家影院都不一樣
Every theater looks different
放映機的光照強度不一樣
They have the lumination on their projector in different level
還有其他的許多原因
or other so many variables
我們真正擔心的改變畫面的東西實際上是放映機
The real alter alternatively from the picture we used to worry about is projections
聲音可大可小
Sounds could be loud and low
演員的頭可能看見也可能看不見
You can see the head of the actor or not
因為放出框了，他們（放映員）挺忙的
Cause they can frame you out, cause they're busy
總有事情要做
They got things to do
可能一卷膠卷發藍，另一捲髮黃
film come up one reel be blue and another reel be brown
都是因為放映機
because use the projector like
我們曾經還挺享受這個，因為是電影的一部分嘛
we got to enjoy that because that's the part of film
我看到印片總是失望
it's always a huge disappointment for me to see a film print
因為真是太讓人鬱悶了
because it's depressing
一點也不清晰，沒個分明的中斷點
it's not sharp, it does not have any snap
搖搖晃晃，髒兮兮，相當可恨
it's shaking, it's dirty, I hate it
我把它放大巨大的顯示幕上
I put it in the tremendous monitor effort
喬司 維克諾，攝影師
（從海底出擊 / 魔鬼總動員 /  星艦戰將）
就是為了我所想像的畫面成真
To make my images the way I have them in mind
我為此製作它們，在攝影機上完成它們
And I create them; I have them on the finish product in the camera
不過看看後來呢
But what happens afterwards
影院裡電影的品質真是慘不忍睹
The quality of film is terrible at theater
每個好萊塢人都會說：
And anybody in Hollywood they say:
“天啊，在攝影機上看著可不是這樣啊”
“Oh, it's not that of camera, no”
所以他們從來不去電影院，看看真正的影院放映是個什麼樣子
so they never go to a theater to see it in the real theater
《鐵達尼號》播放的次數太多了，我們的印片事實上已經脫落了
Titanic plays so long in theaters we actually had our prints fell apart
早些時候從放映機裡掉出來摔碎了
They'd early just dropped out the projectors and in pieces
所以我們絞盡腦汁去獲得更好的放映品質
So we were struggling of trying to get qualities in the theaters
事實是，如果使用數位放映
And out of that came the fact that if it was digital
那效果就很棒了，沒有劃痕，也不會被撕裂
You have a brilliant thing, you wouldn't have to scratch it, you wouldn't have to tear it
…這部電影已經席捲了…
…the movie has been overwhelming…
1999年，我們實現了數位放映《幽靈的威脅》
In 1999, we were able to project phantom menace digitally
2家在紐約，2家在洛杉磯
We have 2 theaters in New York, 2 theaters in LA
那是主流好萊塢電影第一次用數位放映
And that was the first time that major Hollywood movie projected digitally
那時候全國也就40家（數位放映影院）
There were up to 40 there in this country
99年的時候
Just for in 99
2002年，有150家多點
By 2002, there were still over 150
不過已經落後了
The post flow was already there
全都數位化了
it is all digital
所以電影工業的其他也會跟進
And the rest of the industry was going there
聲音已經數位化了，剪輯方式也是
Sound was already got there, Editorial was got there
攝影機卻落後了
The camera is lagging behind
落日殺神，2004
新的公司開始發展高解析度攝影機
New companies began to develop high definition cameras
其他的好萊塢電影也開始跟隨盧卡斯腳步
And the other Hollywood films followed Lucas's lead
邁克爾曼的《落日殺神》使用了湯姆森響尾蛇
Michael Mann's  Collateral used the Thomson viper
這是一架在黑暗環境中優於膠卷攝影機的高解析度攝影機
a HD camera that outperform film in shooting darker enviroments
設備：湯姆森響尾蛇，2004
邁克爾想要在夜裡也能看見
Micheal wants to see into the night
迪奧 畢博，攝影師
（落日殺神 / 綠燈俠 / 芝加哥）
對於數位攝影機來說這是大顯身手的時間
and that point is really best time for digital cameras
把（攝影）邊界推向數位攝影機所擅長的方面
twit up and pushed the boundry on what digital was capable of
《落日殺神》有意思在哪
Collateral is interesting that
它看起來完全是我們所見的那種
it was suppose to look exactly the way it looks
室外的紐約在晚上不是黑的
The New York outside at night you don't see black
你可以看見整個城市有
You see all around the city of
綠色，桃紅，紫色的光和天空的霧靄
Green, magenta, purple lights and haze in the sky
你可以看見所有這些瘋狂的顏色
you just see all these crazy colors
能夠捕捉這樣的影像，只能用數位攝影機
the only way that capture them at that time was digitally
現在都在說晚上攝影的事
you got a lot of this on night talking on photography going now
不過就是用了不同感光度的CCD
this just using the different sensitivities of your CCD chips
晚上能夠捕捉更多的紫外線
it seizes a little more UV spectrum
所以就鼓勵電影人去拍不同的夜景
so you got film makers try to use that to give a different ascetic to night time lighting
不過對我來說這些還是和錄影差不多
(?)but to me it's still of all we're telling the flame of video
響尾蛇攝影機的出現告訴我
the viper was the first camera that really told me that
數位時代強勁崛起
the digital age was right jetting up in a tensity
數位攝影機競爭將隨即而至
I can see the foot race and the cameras coming
2005年，Panavision，膠卷攝影機製造的先驅
In 2005, Panavision, an established force in the film camera business
進行了對單感光元件攝影機的一系列動作
Made a serial push into digital with large sensor of single chip camera
我們開始將這視作一種真正的影片格式
We started looking at this as real format
鮑勃 哈威，Panavision全球市場部高級副總裁
我們覺得最好是我們來設計一台
And we decided the best thing we can do is design
我叫它“能用影帶的膠卷攝影機”
What I used to call it a film camera that takes tape
然後我們開始著手於“Genesis”
And that's when we started drawing up the genesis
設備：Panavision Genesis，2005
“Genesis”具有全幅45mm晶片
“Genesis” is a full frame, 45mm chip
這可以使影像獲得和膠卷相似的景深
that allows depth of field very similar to film
而且可以使用我們的45mm鏡頭
And we can use all our 45mm lenses
總共有上千種
Which total for thousands, literally
我們和索尼合作
And we went to the work partner up to SONY on it
他們負責設計電器元件
they design the electronics and we put it together
接著第一台被用於電影正片製作的
and we introduced the first full frame digital camera
全幅攝影機就誕生了
For making feature films
“Genesis”的畫質超級高，因為潘那維申製造嘛
The “genesis” was high to hell because it's from Panavision
還有潘那維申專用特級系統
And it was so designing A system for Panavision
最好的是還能使用潘那維申的鏡頭
The good about it was it took Panavision lenses
具有全幅感光元件
It was with a 35mm sensor
而“響尾蛇”的只是2/3英吋感光元件
While the viper used 2/3'' sensor
超人再起，2006
人們想獲得和35mm膠卷一樣的感受
people wanted the same feel same look they got from 35mm
“Genesis”能夠做到
which caught what you got with “genesis”
而且畫面超好
And it gave pretty good images
這是我們為電影製作精心設計的
We were very careful to design it for film crews
要是說對比以前有什麼變化
So the transition, if there's going to be one
那就是製作電影更加簡便
Would be easy for the people making movies
迪恩塞姆勒因為《與狼共舞》獲得了學院獎
Dean Semler who was academic award cinematographer, financer of dance with wolves
他在墨西哥拍攝《啟示錄》的時候
Shot  apocalypto down in Mexico
《啟示錄》片場，2006
那的溫度有100（華氏），濕度200
where the tempreture was 100 degrees and humility was 200
而且基本沒變化（不停工）
And never had a second of down time
他感覺這就和攝影機一樣
He felt it was like a film camera
35磅重
It's 35 ponds
他媽的破機器有這麼大
Fucking cameras this big
在頂上還有一個像膠卷盒的東西
And on the top of it, it looks like film magazine
錄影機和機身連在一起
The recorder attached to it
和膠卷盒一樣
The same way the mag will attach at the top on the back
我想看看剛拍了什麼
I want to see what we just got shot
能重播嗎
does it a playback off that?
不能，就和底片一樣
no, you never touch that like original negative
我就直說了
so if you see I get straight
你和索尼在攝影機研發上花了幾百萬
you got to spend how many millions developing camera with SONY
然後你告訴我不能回播
and I can't play the HD back to look at it
因為這是底片嗎？
because that's the negative?
邁阿密風雲，2006，數位拍攝
在06/07年的時候
where we were in those 06, 07
我們已經有了不錯的色度和解析度
we had the color space and the revolution
不過動態範圍還不行
but we didn't have the dynamic range
*動態範圍：亮度反差的範圍*
所以取景的時候一定要小心
so we had to be careful on the sight
動態範圍是硬傷
dynamic range is veto
對我來說動態範圍比什麼都總要
dynamic range is more important than anything to me
這也拖慢了我換數位攝影的進程
so that really me slow down to shoot digitally
看看動態範圍的事吧
if you have thought of the range
要是黑與白本來的感覺是這樣
if the dark and bright is felt like this
從海底出擊，1981，膠卷拍攝
要使用數位拍攝
as shoot in digital
就沒有這麼寬的範圍了
you don't have this wide range
填不滿光亮和黑暗之間的空間
which fill the heights between the blacks and the lights
所以亮些的沒有了
so whatever up here is cut off
暗些的也沒有了
and whatever down there is also cut off
沃利 菲斯特，攝影師
（黑暗騎士 / 全面啟動 / 記憶拼圖）
我就是不知道它怎麼能能讓我達到想要的效果
I just don't feel how it is allowed to enable me to do what I want to do
數位拍攝
你不能指望5檔過度曝光還能看到什麼
you can't overexpose by 5 stops and still have something in the image
你也不能指望4檔曝光不足還能看到些什麼
you can't underexpose it by 4 stops and still have traces in the image
我覺得只能是一片空白
I think you'll find plain in those areas
在2005年，吉姆詹納德，價值數十億的墨鏡和運動服飾公司
in 2005, Jim Jannard, the founder and owner of the multi billion-dollar
Oakley的創始人和擁有者
sunglass and sports apparel company, Oakley
開始製作一架面向影院市場的數位攝影機
set out to create a new cinematic affordable digital camera
吉姆 詹那德，RED數位電影創始人
數位對膠卷不夠尊重
digital wasn't paying enough respect to film
也不如膠卷好
it wasn't as good as film
對我來說一切皆可更好
and to me everything in the world can and will be made better
就看何時何人了
the only question is when and by whom
取代膠卷的運動開始了
there was a technological movements towards the eventual replacement of film
泰德 施洛維茲，RED數位電影
當時的現象就是，主流廠商
what was happening in some of the major manufactures
都想在做自己的HD攝影產品
is they were creating video level tools essentially HD tools
並試圖將其推廣到電影市場
and tried to push that into the cinema
不過我們所看到的是這些產品都差很遠
and what we saw was that it's not any close to good enough
我們想定一個很高的目標，那樣才有意義
we want to set a high enough target so that was meaningful
這就是RED的本質
that's the nature of RED
我們想把膠卷送進養老院
we want to help to send the film to the retirement home
並用更好的來取代它
and have a few good about what took it place
2007年，RED 1面世
in 2007, the RED 1 was available to the public
在這個時代裡，數位攝影機可以拍攝比HD更高的圖元
this new generation, digital cameras could now shoot more resolution than HD
把圖元數目從2K提高到4K
and increased pixels from 2k to 4k
當我看到RED的時候我想我真該給膠卷打個電話：你得來認識一下這傢伙
when I saw the RED I really thought I should call the film on the phone and said: met someone
因為我認為這就是未來
cause I really thought this is the future
切格瓦拉，2008
無論解析度、場景曲線還是看起來的感覺
the resolution, the curve, the way it saw like
都是全新的
I just felt this is a new thing
所以我堅持要用它來拍攝《切格瓦拉》
and I was insisted that we shoot CHE on it
數位技術在一開始很爛，每個人都知道
digital at the beginning was really bad, everybody knew that
維爾莫斯 齊格蒙德，攝影師
（ 越戰獵鹿人 / 激流四勇士 / 雌雄賭徒）
這部比以前的要好
that kind of that camera which was better than previous ones
至少便宜，但是還是不夠好
at least it was cheaper, ok, but it's not good enough
因為總是有經驗不足的問題
actually there is a experience limitation of that
它的確存在問題，它打壓了小廠競爭，它是台電腦
(?)it has problems, it crushed occasion of the mob, it's a computer
但是RED不顧膠卷攝影機的屍體曾經怎樣
but then again RED ignored everything about normal film camera bodies
轉而使用自己覺得正確的東西
and use what they thought was right
最壞的情況也就是
even with the worst stories of being out
因為過熱把所有東西上敷個冰袋
is that the heating had a ice pack on all that stuff
不過我不在乎
none of that bother me
因為得到的實在特別
because the get was so significant
很多天內都不用在100多度的情況下
in this case, not having to log film magazines up and down
用手把膠卷盒拿進拿出
this for days on hand in hundred degree
是不是能用快閃記憶體拍攝不重要
whether they are able to shoot on flash card
換儲存盒只要50秒
change magazines in 50 seconds
這就已經是不錯的冷卻了
that alone was huge frost
也能讓拍出的畫面更好
it resulted in a better movie
*RED 1採用磁碟陣列或CF卡儲存，相對膠卷和錄影帶拍攝時間大大延長*
我很喜歡吉姆詹那德這次的設計，我喜歡他們公司的理念
I really love the Jim Jannard's doing, I love what their company's about
我喜歡他們使用的技術，這不僅僅是
and I love the tech they took, that's very much no holds barred like
“捲起袖子看熱鬧”而已
let's roll up our sleeves let's get it in and up to our eyeballs, let's figure this shit out
社群網戰，2010
RED 1有9磅，加鏡頭14磅
RED 1 is 9 pounds when put up lens on it is 14 pounds
拍《社群網戰》的時候很多時候要拍那些小船
on Social Network I went too many seconds I got to shoot these tiny boats
我覺得它們輕的就像薯片一樣
and I think it's like potato chips
所以我不能把30磅重的設備放到船頂的帆上
and I can't add 30 pounds a camera out on this side sail top on this boat
然後他說：“好吧，你要我怎麼做”
he said “ Ok what you want me to do”
我說：“你自己拿著，或者和別人搭夥
I said “you got to take one, you got to board out you got
不管怎樣你要想出辦法
whatever you got to do you have to figure out the way
給我個印第賽車版的RED 1”
you got to give me the indycar version of the RED 1”
*印地賽車是美國的方程式賽車，相對重量較輕*
這是在週五
this was on Friday
周日他就打電話給我說：
on Sunday, he called me and said:
“我用碳纖做了個機身，你什麼時候來拿，就在我桌上”
“I made one of body in carbon fibers, when you can have about it, it's on my desk”
然後用上的時候，這東西只有5磅半
and went down, and pick up to it and they were 5 and a half pounds
這在電影業中從未出現過
that never existed before for film cameras
這麼快的回應
this sort of immediate calling responds
在電影製作人和攝影機製作人之間
between the people who are shooting and the people who are creating the cameras
貧民百萬富翁，2008
我迫切的想要製作點充滿新鮮空氣的東西
I was desperate to make something that had all the fresh air in
尤其是你去印度孟買的時候
and cause when you go to India in Bombay especially
鮮活的生命氣息撲面而來，對你狂叫著
it's got life, it's just coming screaming on you all the time in everywhere
丹尼激動的產生了一個想法，我們應該在劇本中
Danny come to an idea, rage, come to an idea of speed energy use
用到速度和活力的元素
and that's what we need on the script
跑，對，這就是我們要在印度用的
and then running, that's it, that's we use in India
那真是世界上最神奇的地方
it's just the most wonderful place of the world
我們想要製作一部與眾不同的電影，如果攝影機能實現那一點的話
for a different kind film we wanted the camera would trying somehow catch a bit of that
就是要找一部攝影機，任務明確了
it's about finding camera, the task is there, it's clear
我要做的就是用我狂妄自大又符合正統的經驗去找到一件工具
my job is to find, with all my anarchic and conventional experience there, to find a tool
設備：矽映 SI-2K，2007
像矽映SI-2K這樣的攝影機
cameras like Silicon Imaging SI-2K
可以到達對於膠卷攝影機和早期
have been able to go places and get shots that
高解析度攝影機非常難以到達的地點進行拍攝
would have been very difficult with film or earlier versions of HD cameras
這裡有個電腦感光元件在後面
it's a sensor of computer back on it
你想要把攝影機做的看起來像電腦一樣嗎
so do you make a computer look like a film camera?
或者你會把攝影機線拔掉，和筆記型電腦連接在一起？
or do you say: “the hell of that, take this and ease that cable and connected into a laptop”
這就是SI攝影機的本事
and that will be the SI camera was
單憑這點世界上還沒有如此之小的攝影機能夠做到
at that point no one camera in the world is small enough
阿里 普萊斯勒，矽映總裁
安東尼想要在大街上追著孩子們跑
Anthony wanted to run into the streets and track the children as they were running
還得是和小孩一樣的高度
and be as the same height level as the kids
所以他們把筆記型電腦帶上裝包裡
so they took macbook pros and put them into a bag pack
用作捕捉和記錄的系統
to use for their capture and recording system
膠卷攝影機，就算從穩固架或起重機上卸下來
film cameras, even when off the legs or off the steadicam or off the crane
還是要和攝影者的身體連接在一起
still connected on the camera man's body
他或者就這麼追著你跑
he's either chasing you down the street
或者把東西架在這然後轉身帶著那一大堆東西回來
or he's got it here, or he turns round and runs back with things like that
不過用SI-2K就動能做到
with this SI-2K you can do that
因為它不再連著攝影者的身體了
it's no longer connected to the camera man's body
你能做好多其他的事
you can do different things with that
在片場可以真正做到“自由發揮”
during the scene it's just literally improvising
2009年，《貧民百萬富翁》獲得了最佳攝影學院獎
in 2009, slum dog millionaire won the academic award for best cinematography
這是該獎項第一次頒發給幾乎全程使用數位技術拍攝的電影
it was the first time that award was giving to a movie shot almost entirely on digital camera
所以既然您獲得了學院獎
so you had the academic award
您覺得數位拍攝是否已經被主流接受了呢
so do you feel like that the film make digital be accepted by the main stream now?
《貧民》在評論界和觀眾當中的成功
the success of the slum dog with critics and audience
代表了一個時代的某些特點
symbolizes something of an epoque
也算是為數位拍攝打定了基礎
it perhaps puts hammers and stakes a little bit in the ground
這樣看來數位格式已經被接受了
this far was acceptance of digital format
這是第一個對大規模使用數位技術的獎項
it was the first really acknowledgement on the large scale of digital
為此我非常為安東尼高興
I was very pleased for Anthony for that
因為我以為他會覺得他永遠也不能拿到這個獎
because I think he felt it was some acknowledgement he would never arrive at
因為他是如此特立獨行於數位世界
because he's chosen to specialized too much in the digital world
不過現在他的成就改變了所有人的看法
I think that was where he goes and everybody changed
頭號公敵，2009
設備：SONY F23
第九禁區，2009
泰特羅，2009
設備：SONY F23
爆料大師，2009
設備：RED 1
阿凡達，2009
設備：SONY F950
《阿凡達》本來是我在《鐵達尼號》之後的下一部電影
avatar was gonna be my next movie after titanic
所以在99年的時候我想把它拍成3D的
so I converted to think about it shoot in 3D in ‘99
我立刻就想到能在未來拍攝3D的唯一方法就是數位拍攝
I knew immediately that the only way to shoot 3D, the future of shooting 3D is digital
我們做了個實驗，我們把2部高解析度攝影機並排放在一塊
we're starting to an experiment, we took 2 HD cameras side by side
我覺得結果還是相當酷的
I thought the result was pretty cool
接著我就和佩斯合作建立起了自己的攝影系統
then with Pace I built the vision camera system
一台攝影機放在這，另一台放到頂端
we've decided to put one camera here and another camera on top
那應該怎麼整合這兩個呢
so what happened in here to marry this two
因為從觀測上說是需要兩個畫面的對吧？
cause there scopicly you need two images exist right?
沒錯
correct
我們有一個問題就是在攝影機較大的時候
one of the problems we have was the larger camera is a fact
我們不能像我們兩眼位置一樣把他們並排放置
that we wouldn't put them side by side like your 2 eyeballs, right
文森 佩斯，卡佩3D技術CEO
你不能在現實世界把兩架攝影機這麼放
you couldn't put those cameras physically in that position
他們會撞到的
they will run in to each other
所以我們利用鏡面反射
so we use reflect of a mirror
這樣在你的腦海裡
and then that allows us to overlaid the 2 camera systems
兩架攝影機的實際位置可以重疊
of your imagine form a physical stand point
而這樣就不再有兩眼間距離的限制
where there is no limitation how close we get these eyes together
而這一點對3D來說是非常重要的
and that's really important to 3D
要製作3D效果
to create 3D
兩架攝影機要像兩隻眼睛一樣
2 cameras works a pair just like our 2 eyes
從稍微不同的角度獲取畫面
they capture pictures from slightly different angle
從而製造三維空間的深度和廣度
providing the sense in 3 dimensional depth and distance
我有個圈內笑話
I have a joke of most people all around me
我屬於平面世界
I long for when the world was flat
因為不止適應系統要互相複製
because it's not only the cameras system duplicated
製作流程上的每件事都要相互複製
everything duplicates down the chain, right
一個鏡頭控制另一個鏡頭
so lensing control over lensing
很多人說這要加倍的難搞，實際上不對
and a lot people said that's as twice as hard than that's incorrect statement
不止是這樣
that's more than that
因為兩架攝影機要像完全分不出來的雙胞胎那樣工作
because these 2 cameras have to operate like sign-missed twins
他們必須完美的複製對方
they have to mimic each other perfectly
如果電影製作完成一切正常的話
I think when films are done right and when it really works is when
你會覺得身臨其境，自己就在那個旅程之中，完全進入在情節裡
you feels I'm there, I'm in this journey and immerged the story line
對我來說最有趣的地方在於把這個工具交給真正的創造之手
the fun part for me is to really get this tools in the creative hands
這樣就有人帶你去你從未想像過的地方了
so people can really take you to place that you never imagine before
《阿凡達》出來的時候我真的很驕傲於它的畫面，太棒了
Avatar came out and I was really proud of those images, look gorgeous
緊接著《愛麗絲夢遊仙境》和《馴龍高手》也上映了
and it was followed up by Alice to wonderland and how to train your dragon
邦邦邦，市場上接二連三出現了3部3D電影
boo boo boo, 3 movies on the markets one after another and all of them were (?)
而且都是年度票房大戶
the 3 of them were the top grossing films of the year
所以突然間大門敞開了
so all of a sudden the door just blow wide open on the whole thing
人們看到了這裡的市場前景
people really saw the potential of this as a market
電影消費提升了觀眾
this consumptions of films has increased our audiences
的觀影品味和理解能力
both appetite for them and now knowledge of them
所以想要製作驚人之作越來越難了
so therefore it's getting harder and harder to impress
這就是3D為什麼這麼流行的原因之一
it's one of the reasons why 3D's taking off
換個口味看電影而已
just a way looking at a film
演員如同一尊雕塑，就是會走會動呼之欲出
the actor is like a sculpture or something only it's moving and comes out
就像從劇院到電影，從無聲到有聲之類的一樣
and like a combination when theater went film, music and everything
我恨3D，我帶上了眼鏡會覺得反胃
I hate 3D, I put on those glasses and I get sick in my stomach
黑的什麼也看不清
it's too dark looking through them
整個的3D現象實際上就是他媽的市場炒作難道不是嗎？
the whole 3D phenomenon is a marketing fucking scheme isn't it?
作為一個旁觀者我可以肯定的說
I can safely say as a viewer
我完全不感興趣
I'm totally uninterested in it
丁點興趣也沒有
I'm without any interests whatsoever
我覺得這就是一時火爆
I think it's a fad
早晚燒個精光
I think it will burn out
電影工作室把什麼都做成3D是不明智的
the studio's not wise to slap 3D on everything
《阿凡達》之所以做成3D是有原因的
with Avatar there is a reason this movie is in 3D
它要給你一種體驗
because it's taking you on an experience
不是為了賺錢、嘩眾取寵或者玩把戲
it isn't something that was on for money or a joke or a gimmick
因為它是被創作成那個樣子的
it's there because it was created that way
《阿凡達》結合了兩種完全不同的電影製作方式
Avatar is 2 completed different forms of film making combine
我們只實際拍攝了1/3的內容
we only use lenses for about 1/3 of the movement
都是普通的東西
it all sets in just normal stuff
燈光，佈景，拍5場
(?)lighting, mural, 5 action
其餘的2/3是特效
it was virtual FX to the other 2/3
我們從來沒去真的叢林，我們創造了一個叢林
we never shot a real jungle, we have create a jungle
都是建模
it's all peer modeling
每個草葉每隻蹦來蹦去的蟲子
every blade of grass, every bug bouncing around
沒有一個是真實叢林的場景
not one foot film shot in a real jungle
數學建模能完美創造真實世界
you have this idea that you could hold a mathematically perfect model for creating reality
只要電腦和軟體就好
you just threw on the computing power at it, you just put software on it
我們就是這麼幹的，我們要求
cause it's all we found, we required
藝術家和攝影師研究光在物體上如何反射
artist and people who trained in photography looking at how light interact with those things
然後以此為基礎寫程式碼，創造一個看起來很逼真的世界
to figure out how to write the code, to make it look real
數位操控帶給眼睛的幻覺
what I find was that the manipulations the digital made your eyes to do
的確很引人入勝但卻很空洞
they are all seductive but alternately a little bit hollow
我常用的一個比喻是我想起有個夏天
the analogy I used t use was I remember the summer when
玉米油可以讓巧克力餅乾很軟
chips oil give these chocolate cookies (?) soft
這很不錯啊，讓餅乾變軟
that's amazing, just soft cookie and
不過幾個月過後
and then after a couple of months
在上面的完全是一坨化學XX
what's on it is some horrible chemical crap
開始只是給了你美好的幻想
give you bad illusion it fooled you first
我所擔心的是現在大規模使用CGI
my concern is that the image alternately with CGI
我們的年輕人也許不會再相信電影螢幕上的任何東西了
I don't know the younger generation is believing anything anymore on screen
都不是真實的
it's not real
你呈現了一個感覺真實卻完全不是真實的世界
you are presenting complete unreality and make them feel like it was real
甚至都先於拍攝任何真實場景…
and before it was captured in reality…
好吧，你也進過不少片場吧
alright, you've been on a couple of movie sets
真實過嗎
when was it ever real?
一堵牆，什麼也沒有
there was a kind of wall, there is nothing over there
30個人忙忙碌碌
there were 30 people stand around
一個拿著麥克風，一個在梯子上的人把屁股溝露出來了(=  =)
a guy with a boom mic, the other guy upon a ladder with his ass crack hanging out
還有個起重機，紐約的夜晚可能是伯班克的白天
there is a sit crane, your street night exterior New York was a day exterior Burbank
哪裡真實了？
what was it ever real
駭速快手，2008
在老的拍攝技法中我們更為靈活
we are free of the old technology of capturing images
攝影機，膠卷，鏡頭，曝光
camera, film, lens, exposure
我能掌控很多，有更多選擇，更多點子
it give me more control, more choice, more wits
去達成腦中的想像
to access what you are imagining in your head
哈利波特與混血王子，2009
特效分解
電腦技術只能越來越好
computers will only get better and better
你能夠把任何東西創造的足夠真實
will be able to produce anything you want completely realistic
而且換個想法，如果時間足夠，你也可以融入到那個世界
and alternately, if you got enough time, the world is all yours there
魔戒二部曲：雙城奇謀，2003
三百壯士，2006
神鬼奇航：世界盡頭，2007
守護者，2009
你要抓緊學習抓住自己的想像
you have to try to outpace study and seize your imagination
做出人們從沒見過的東西，而這樣的東西一年比一年更真實
do something they haven't seen before and every year it getting more and more real
諸神之怒，2010
特效分解
藝術家和電影製作者在不斷提升畫面的內涵、視覺效果和真實性
the artiest and the film maker are constantly trying to up the immanence spectacle and realism
所以現在的情況是從來沒出現過的
so that really put this in a positions of like never before
同時拓展了藝術和技術
really having to wide technology and art
數位技術真的很厲害
that was great about the digital technology
一兩年內就可能再上一階
it should doubled in everything in one or two years
你想做什麼只要想好
once you set your mind on that path
一切變的容易，不過是時間的問題
it all becomes very simple, it just be a matter of time
因為數位技術在不斷進步
cause digital is gonna continue to improve
攝影機公司像RED、阿萊、索尼和其他的
camera companys like RED, ARRI, SONY and others
在不斷改進自己的商品
are constantly developing new products continue to make advances
讓它們在動態範圍、解析度和顏色上有更好表現
on dynamic range, resolution and color
我喜歡看這些廠商競爭
I love that all these manufactures are competing against each other
把大攝影機做的更小、更快、更便宜、感光更好
to make big cameras smaller, faster and cheaper, better sensored
最近數位攝影機的
with dynamic range of digital camera
動態範圍卡在10段
up until recently have been limited to really match to 10 stop
設備：RED EPIC
不過在EPIC或ALEXA上你不用擔心這個問題
but you don't see that problem in the EPIC or the ALEXA
設備：ARRI ALEXA
數位攝影機的動態範圍已經比原來好多了
the dynamic range was much better when I was use to with digital
90年代中期的時候，ARRI生產的還全是傳統化學底片攝影機
up untill the mid-90s, for ARRI, it was all photo chemical
葛籣 康奈，ARRI - 首席技師
當我覺得數位技術已經成熟
we solve the digital technology mature to a point that were
我們也開始發展自己的數位攝影機
we began and invite the digital technology
我們用在ALEXA上的感光元件
the sensor that we used now on the ALEXA camara
設備：ARRI ALEXA，2010
讓我們驕傲的說，其拍攝品質足以製作電影正片
allowed us to offer a camera that we can proudly promote as a feature film camera
ALEXA擁有所有令我們興奮的元素
the ALEXA takes all of that we are excited about
在電影製作中可以帶來膠卷具有的質感
in film making and brings those textural qualities that film has
及熟悉的色彩表現
brings that definitely familiar color space
最近我才對ALEXA感興趣，因為他是ARRI的新產品
and only recently I'm realy interested in ALEXA made by Arriflex not heard
而且和用膠卷拍攝沒什麼不同
that it's like shooting film with digital format
非要我使用數位拍攝的話
if I'm push to shoot on digital
我會用ALEXA，因為可以得到很好的效果
I will take the ALEXA and that could help me get good result
雨果，2011
設備：ARRIALEXA
落日車神，2011
驚悚末日，2011
設備：ARRIALEXA
時間規劃局，2011
這是RED的新產品，我們叫它EPIC
this is the new RED, we just call it EPIC, so
信不信由你，可是比RED 1提高了60%的圖元
this is, believe it or not, 60% more resolution than the RED 1
吉姆詹那德給我看他的新產品EPIC
when Jim Jannard showed me the EPIC
我看著它說：“等等，
I looked at it and I said: “ wait a minute
“這個能幹什麼？
“what did that do?
“能怎麼幫助你說故事？”
“how could that free you as a story teller”
龍紋身的女孩，2011
設備：RED EPIC
超凡蜘蛛人，2012
它能拍攝非常美麗、豐富、
this camera created those beautiful, rich,
自然或者說格調獨特的顏色
very natural or very stylisticly wonderful colors
哈比人，2012
設備：RED EPIC
我們要用解析度4K的放映機在超大螢幕上放映
we've taken a digitally projective 4k images on a gigantic screen
那效果一定震人心魄
and it is absolutely mind-blowing
影院的運輸方式要改變了
the delivery system of cinema is going to change
這比攝影機本身更令我興奮
and that's actually more exciting a way for me beside the actual camera
因為那種老掉牙的一套：
cause the ancient system of
送電影上卡車，到不同的城市，再卸貨
film on a truck driving into a city and unloading it
要被取代了
that being replaced
運送巨大的膠卷鐵盒子到處跑是相當費錢的
the old way of having ship giant film case around is very very expensive
所以人們意識到如果使用數位放映
so the business realized that there was a tremendous possible savings
可以省一大筆錢
in digital delivery and digital projection
我們都想要母片，底片的第一版
we are all want the pristine print, first print of all the negative
不過這不可能
but we cannot have that
你必須拷貝
so you have to copy it
但是用數位放映就沒必要拷貝了
and the advance of DCP is not real copying
掃描完成後不需要複印
once it scanned, it doesn't get copied again
更像是克隆，完全一樣的東西
it's cloned, so it's exactly the same thing
我對數位放映機更有好感
I'm getting more impressed with digital projection
我不是技術帝
as much as…I'm not big on technology
但我覺得數位放映機的發展前景是極好的
I think digital projections will come a long way
過去的兩年我們賣了10000台數位放映機到影院
in the last 2 years we've sold 10,000 digital projectors into cinemas
全球都在換
the conversion is taking place globally
現在我們已經完成了50%
we were probably 50% or more there
剩下的很快就會完成
and the rest of the conversion will happen very quickly
既然令人驚歎的電影已經製作出來
they produce gorgeous pictures
那麼我們就必須創造更好的表現方式
and you had to study building up a wave
所以我們要讓數位螢幕在2015年達到200000塊
that's why we're gonna up to 200,000 digital screens by 2015
傳統的印片方式岌岌可危
the model for printing film is endangered
但我不希望最終膠卷也是這樣
and ultimately I hope that it doesn't take film with it
小時候去看電影
as a kid, I went to the movies
坐下後看到紅色的幕簾
you sat down and looked at a big red curtain
接著幕簾拉開
and then that curtain parted
電影就開始了
and there is the movie was going to begin right?
巴瑞 萊文森，導演
（恐怖海灣 / 少年福爾摩斯 / 雨人）
然後你驚呼：“天啊，真妙！”
and you went “oh, my gosh! oh, this is special!”
這是我童年時代的印象
that's my childhood image
如今這已經不是絕妙的事了
it's not special anymore
別的事取代它了
it's another thing
一個世紀以來電影院都跟教堂似的
in a way cinema was a church between a century
因為同樣是很多人進到一個又大又黑的房間
because we come to this large dark room and sit
看著螢幕想這會是個什麼故事
looked up and think what it would tell you
卡薩布蘭卡，1942
好多關於穿衣、行為、怎麼討好女人和怎麼扮演英雄
enormous amount how to dress how to act be with woman how to act hero
那個時代的螢幕很不同
something is extraordinary about the scene
有40英呎高
at that age is 40 feet high
那麼大一塊螢幕
and in 40 feet high,
相對日常生活很多事都變得神奇起來
something mythic about it is beyond your everyday life
寬度也很廣，應該有80英呎
it's so much big huge span, it should be 80 feet wide
觀眾會被螢幕包圍
you should envelop the audience in the screen
因為那才是電影院.....對！ 那才是電影院
cause that's cinema--yeah, that's cinema
聲音也每時每刻包圍著你
and the sound around you every minute
我真是不明白為什麼有人喜歡在電腦上看電影
I mean why people want to watch movies on their computers I should never know
我經常在地鐵上看到有人用iPhone看電影，我就會想…
I see people watch movies on their iphone in subway all the time…
“別這樣作！”
and I went “---no!!!”
有人說這不是好事，不過也不一定非有那麼糟
who might say this is bad, it doesn't have to be bad
晚上我妻子睡了，我睡不著
late at night, my wife sleeps and I can't sleep
我就會拿起我的iPhone
and I put my xx on my iphone
再帶上副不錯的耳機，把螢幕幾乎貼臉的看電影
put up good headphone and watch films close to my face
這很有趣
and this sound interesting about that
一切都很私人
you‘ve got everything very privately
所以挺懷念想哭的卻不想人看見的時候
I think it was missing I want to cry without people seeing it
我放《鋼木蘭》的時候哭了
I want to cry without people seeing it, I'll put the steel Magnolias
要是我妻子醒了，我只好暫停，再藏到枕頭裡
and I cry and if my wife wakes up I just get pause and put it under a pillow
這很有趣
and get something interesting about that
因為以前不可能有機會經歷
because you didn't have a chance to experience before
萊娜 杜漢，演員/導演
（微型傢俱）
約會已經不會有人問“去看電影吧”
You can ask on a date no body's like “let's get on the movies” any more
甚至現在已經是這樣的
I don't even felt that's going on, I felt like
人們會說“我們在床上看看Netflix有什麼吧”
people like “let's watch something on Netflix streaming on my bed” which
*Netflix：相當於掌上影院*
然後一群24歲的年輕人就在床上等著
was 24 years old guys waiting to get you sit on their bed
不過這確實是正在發生的事情
but I think that's what's happening
我能看到正在上映的電影，能從平板電腦或其他的什麼上看任何電影
I can get any on movie I can get any movie from pad or anything
對我來說再自然不過，坐下就看
That's naturalest thing to me I can sit down and watching
不過會錯過很多細節，那就沒法感受電影的魅力了
but you will not see all the detail that you won't be able to feel it
比如說就沒法感受…
like if you be able to feel…
我的高解析度電視大著呢
my big HDTV is 20 big
你是說和女孩子親熱這類的東西嗎？
You mean go to see make up with girls like that
沒興趣，我早過了那個年齡了
But that, no, I'm way past that
真的嗎？
Are you sure?
相信我啦
Believe me
看電影的方式越來越多
So many different way for watching movie
分享經歷的方式
That sharing experience aspect to it
正在改變看去影院看電影的習慣
That shifting, going to the movies
也很大程度上變得虛擬了
Well it's also becoming much larger virtually
可視世界已經大大像虛擬化延伸了
Mural space was definitely spanned virtually
大家在虛擬世界裡分享電影
So they're watching movies together in this sort of virtual worlds
幾乎是不可避免的
And that will be inevitable
費洛蒙也要虛擬交換嗎？
You had to get the Pheromone to exchange virtually
啊？ 怎麼流血怎麼流汗，不接觸怎麼爽啊
Yeah? how do you bleed and sweat and be comfortable without getting together
你在影院做那些嗎？穿著拉風風衣？
You do that in the theater? In your trench coat
倒沒有，不過可以一起笑一起哭啊
No but laughing together and crying together
有時候虛擬的經驗反而更加奏效
Some way the virtual experience is more rewarding because
因為總有實際的溝通在進行
There is a actual dialog going on
這些20多歲的小伙子不在乎
So these 20-year-old does not care
不過在網路社交空間倒有很多影院
But there are lots of cinemas in the communal space
他們只談論在臉書還是什麼上又交了什麼好友
There they just sit in and tell a story getting friends on Facebook or whatever it is
你得適應，你要適應不了也沒事
You got to go with it, if you can't be able to deal with it
因為你的時代已經過去了
that's fine, because it means your time is finished
大家看開點吧
it's time for all the people to take it on
30歲以下的年輕人
the kids, 30 and under
在電腦電視上看了無數的數位影像
have seen endless digital image on their computer, on their television
對於他們來說，那就是他們的電影
and that to them is their film
我曾經希望這些小型攝影機
I just had hoped that these little cameras
可以促成民間電影的一場革命
will make a revolution where you would say the folk films good
不過自己製作的話
Just do it ourselves
許多才華和人才都因為免費而得不到足夠尊重
so a lot of talent and stuff could be free by less respect
全民都在解讀電影
Everyone is interpreting
他們透過鏡頭和畫面解讀事實或者自以為的事實
Their reality or what they did their reality through an image, through a lens
不過有些孩子真的還挺擅長這個的
And some kids are really good at it, I'll tell you
微型傢俱，2010
設備：佳能 7D
我熱愛DV文化，否則我也不會拍這部電影
I love digital video culture, or I won't never making with this
因為我是作家出身，而我認為
Because I came out as a writer and I thought that as
電影製作人應該是有專業知識
you have certain kind of knowledg
然後可以自由操控
and basically my head keeps a thought like a dude
拍攝機器的那麼一個人
who operational machine to do this job
我覺得真踏上那條路我會害怕的
I think I would be scared to step into that road
巨大的攝影機和15人的燈光團隊
If it had to involve getting a huge camera and get a 15 lightening technicians together
我覺得用這樣小而且私人的方式體驗電影製作就可以了
I was able to experience making movies small private way which I need to do
佳能5D和其他單眼相機如何呢
What about the 5Ds, what about the DLSRs
這些相機是給記者設計的
These cameras are designed to the request of APM writers
攝影師可以拍攝新聞影片給網站
So there news photographers could shoot news video for their websites
僅此而已
That's it
人們會覺得
then people came along went:
“哇，還不錯，我也要用”
“woo, I like the look of that, I'm gonna use that”
然後效果也不錯
And it can work
不過拍電影可不行 --  為什麼？
but I hate it being used as movie cameras -- Why?
不夠好
It's not good enough
但是它們便宜，人人都能拍電影
But they ain't expensive, people can make movies
如果我是藝校的學生，有台Canon 7D或5D
If I've been in art school and I have a Canon 7D or 5D
那肯定很棒
It would be wonderful
你今晚用什麼拍？
What are you shooting on tonight?
7D。天，7D耶
-7D. Oh my God, that's 7D
是為了研二的作業
For my second year of grad film
我猜是因為易用，拍的不賴，而且不貴
I guess it's accessible, give you a lot that you can capture, but it's not super expensive
舒提 甘古利，紐約大學研究生
我用7D或5D拍攝主要是預算原因
I want to shoot with the 7D or 5D primarily for budget reasons
還因為只有一周時間可用了
And because we are given a week in which we have to shoot our film
大部分時間都花在了選題、約場地
And in amount of time we were lose in terms like changing film checking the gate
所以時間不夠用也是原因
And then I would probably not be able to film the soon I want to
想要講自己的故事變得比較便宜
It becomes the very cheap way for us to tell our stories about ourselves
它已經跳脫了與環境抗爭的藝術載體
It takes this art format out of where fighting environment
很多人都加入了藝術創作的行列
and a lot more people to make art
人人都有紙和筆
Everybody and his little brother has a piece of paper and pencil
但偉大的故事又...
But how many great stories had been written
在這紙上寫出多少呢
on that piece of paper
現在同樣的事要發生在電影身上了
Now the same thing is gonna happen in cinema
幾個電影人聚在一起
There used to be in conference when film making guys
坐在咖啡店閒談
people sat in coffee shop and saying
說如果有機會，自己會製作多麼偉大的電影
What great film they would make if the man would ever give me a chance
現在好了，人人有機會，放手去做就行
It was kind of great when the day came that it was we go do it
現在每個人都能做電影，電影遍地開花，這不錯
Everybody can make a movie now, movies are everywhere, that's a good thing
我不這麼認為，其實好處少
I don't think so actually, there's less good
壞處多
There's more bad
因為每個人都想做什麼做什麼
because everybody is able to do whatever they want to do
真是民主，真是不錯
That's democratization out there, that's fantastic
但是我們的下一代會吃苦頭的
But I think my kids will suffer
他們再不會享受到我們成長時期所擁有的品質了
they will not have the qualities we have been growing up
因為不會再有人…
Cause there isn't somebody there…
不會再有人在乎品味了
There isn't a taste make involved
天啊！
Wow!
膠卷已經完了嗎？您怎麼看
Is this the end of film? What do you think?
我覺得，賽璐珞仍然會是個選項
I think celluloid is still gonna be a choice
大藝術家，2011，膠卷攝製
魔球，2011，膠卷攝製
不可能的任務：鬼影行動，2011，膠卷攝製
生命樹，2011，膠卷攝製
戰馬，2011，膠卷攝製
饑餓遊戲，2012，膠卷攝製
黑暗騎士：黎明昇起，2012，膠卷攝製
轉變只因為有一個新的選擇
a transition starts with people offering a new choice
不過是否意味著舊的選擇即將被取代
But if it finished it will take the old choice away
我不認為現在的技術已經準備好了
I don't think techniques are ready to do that yet
我們有100多年純粹用膠卷拍攝的歷史
we have hundred years of experience basically shooting on film
而現在膠卷也還在使用
And film it still around
不管喬治盧卡斯說什麼“膠卷已死”
No matter what George Lucas said that “film is dead”
他其實20年前就這麼說了
he said that 20 years ago
但是膠卷沒有死，人們還是喜歡用膠卷
But film is not dead because people like to shooting on film
因為膠卷真的可以呈現難以置信的美
because it really has an incredibly beautiful look
誰在乎啊
Who cares
20年內他們就不會再說膠卷怎樣怎樣
In 20 years from now they wouldn't be saying what looks like film
轉而說“看看我的數位攝影機能做什麼吧”
they would be saying “look what I can do with my digital”
我會是最後還在使用膠卷攝影的人
I will be the one last guy shooting film
因為沒其他人使用它了
Cause no one else would be left shooting film
而且我確定在10年間我也會開始使用數位技術
But I certain will be use digital technology within the next 10 years
我希望，要是5到10年內膠卷還存在的話
I hope, if in another 5 or 10 years film still exists
我還是打算繼續用膠卷拍
I still plan to shoot on film
膠卷時代是不是結束了？
Is it the end of film?
對，我猜它是完了
Yeah, I guess it is
而且我認為5年之內，膠卷就...
And I think in 5 years, film will be
膠卷就幾乎不會存在了
film will be exception, I really do
膠卷設備銷售在2007年達到了頂峰
Film production peaked in 2007
比爾 羅素，ARRI攝影部副總裁
我們在那時膠卷攝影機已經生產過剩10%了
Our factory at that time was working 110% to produce film cameras
然後呢？
Then what happened?
然後世界變了
Then the world changed
所有的訂單都變成數位的了
New purchases are all digital
膠卷攝影機可以延續數十年
Film cameras can last for decades
仍能使用也仍被使用
They will be still available and in use
然而，主流廠商
However, our major manufactures
已經停止新膠卷攝影機的發展
have seized the development of new film cameras
“結束了，ARRI、Panavision的膠卷攝影機”
“電影攝影機公司已靜靜停止生產膠卷攝影機”
他們不再生產膠卷攝影機了
They no longer make them
我們不得不和賽璐珞說再見了
We will have to say goodbye to celluloid
膠卷會消失
it will go away I'm afraid
“膠卷像影機，1888-2011”
因為某些特殊用途它們還是會存在
And they will be cared for special occasions
但是其他的都要變了
I think, but it's gonna change
一旦這個選擇消失了
once that option is gone
嗯
Right
一旦現在的年輕人不再有膠卷電影的體驗
Once young people don't have the experience
我覺得我們正在經歷這場全面變革
I think we are living through this total transformation
我覺得大概人們都會擔心這會是沒完沒了的爭論
I think in general people will fear it's just endless noise
沒人說得清什麼是好的，什麼是不好的
no one was able to tell what's good or bad
沒人能真正做出好東西
No one will be able to make good things
所有好的都會消失
And good things will just get lost
我覺得我們的文化繼承岌岌可危
That in danger I think, the continuation of our culture
一切歸於塵土
What will back to me need to back to the wild
嗯
Right
你從哪裡獲得文化、藝術和知識的養份呢？
Where did you get the nourishment of culturally, artistically, intellectually
哪裡呢？
Where did you get it
電影製作的關鍵一步是存檔
And an important step of movie making process is archival
把成片和其他資料儲存起來
Storing the final complete movie and materials used to create it
沒人把存檔當回事
Nobody takes archival seriously
人們都把東西存在硬碟裡
They're all save it on hard drive
放了一年再拿出來
And if the hard drive on the shelf and a year later
放的時候可能就出現“噠噠噠”的聲音
You load it, it just got “ter…ter…”
因為卡住了
Because they stick
它不會總是這樣
You don't find them all time they stick
不過要是你發現了
If You do find out all the time
那就是壞了，然後噠噠響
they wear out and go “ter…ter…”
1950年代起，在電視廣告開始興盛的時期
Since the early 1950s, since the advance of the commercial television
邁克爾 五井，攝影師，美國攝影師協會主席
有80多種影片格式
There had been 80 formats of video
現在這80多種影片格式
Today, these 80 formats of video
的大多數已經完全不能播放了
most cannot be played anymore
就因為播放器已經不存在了
Cause the machine simply don't exist
拍電影的時候我們會把樣片做2個數位備份
When we make a movie we have 2 digital copies of all of the dailys
你把這些拷貝裝箱的時候
When you box those how to be stored
最好放個播放器在旁邊
Yet put a reader in with that thing
我有8種80年代做的音樂短片和廣告存檔格式
I have archival 8 formats for music video and commercials I did n 1980s
已經沒機器能播了
And there's no machine that can play them
在數位世界你完全找不到
There are no archives or formats or anything
任何實體存檔格式
in the digital world that you will put any stock in
所以數位格式的存檔問題含待解決
so their archive issues are simply not being dealt with yet
對於電影
The only thing you can sure of the on film
或其他的動態影像來說
or anything of the moving image
你能保證儲存個六七十年的
is gonna be around may by for 60 or 70 years from now
很有趣也很諷刺
Interestingly enough, ironically enough
只有賽璐珞
The celluloid
蓋瑞 因豪斯，柯達首席技術官
膠卷是特別的
Film is unique
因為膠卷同時是捕捉和儲存介質
Because film is a capture medium and an storage medium
所以你要回看的話
So if you really want to go back
只要保存得當
and if you can restore it in the right conditions
100年後只要有光
A hundred years later all you have to do is shining light through it
也還是可以看
And you are able to see it
不會有格式淘汰的問題
There were never be format obsolete
愛德 斯塔拉德曼，動態影像助理館長
喬治 伊斯特曼博物館（世界最古老的攝影博物館和影片藏館）
1909年
There was a conference in 1909
膠卷的規格和標準被整理確定
Where they put together the standard for film
102年未變
While it hasn't changed for 102 years
我用氮氣保存的膠卷
I have a film in my nitrogen forms
現在仍能在放映機上放映
I can pull it out and run it on the projector today
儘管我知道這是1895年拍攝完成的
even know it was made in 1895
如果換個觀點，想想存檔
If the point, alternately the archiving is
可以是原始作品的完全複製
the faithful reproduction of the original product
那電影人現在有更好的機會
Film makers now have a better chance
讓自己的作品可以
of something I may being showed properly 50 years from now
在50年後仍完美展現
that I ever have in history
可人們總說“我們可不知道50年後會發生什麼
people keep saying “we don't know what's going to happen in 50 years,
“也許就沒法播放了
“we don't know how to read the information or
“也許就毀損了，你必須轉換它要不就沒有了”
“it's going to decay, you have to migrated or it will die”
對，沒錯，得轉換，不過還有一件事
yeah, sure, you will, and some of the those things are true
這樣的解決方案總比膠卷好
all of them are better scenario than film
幾乎這世界上的所有東西
all of everything in this whole world
都在用數位儲存
is stored digitally
是啊
yeah
對啊，問題就在這裡
Yeah, there are problems with it
但是問題是可以被解決的
But they are gonna solve those problems
這點我保證
I'll guarantee that
這麼多的數位資訊
There's too much digital information out there
不可能沒有更全面的儲存解決辦法
not to figure out a full proof way to storage forever
歷史總是在進步
Archeology always improves
某些我們無法控制的變化
So as the way we lose things change
也許正是我們找到解決方案的契機
The way that we invent to find them changes
所以您並不擔心這些消失的東西囉
So you are not worried about all these disappearing
如果某件事對人類真的是重要的
Is things are important for human beings
那就肯定會有保存的辦法
we figure out a way to preserve them
這總是沒錯的
It's always been truth
這是我們生活的一部分
Yes we do that part of life
有一天我們也許會在舞臺上展示電影膠卷
We might get to the stage where a print of a film
因為稀有而使它更像一件藝術品
Is so rare is almost like an art object
而我們可以說：
And we can go back and say
“這是一份電影膠卷，全世界唯一一份”
“this is actually a print of film and it's the only one of the world.”
一兩百年後這些都不會剩下任何痕跡
100, 200 years from now there won't be a trace of this left
我們現在所製造的東西也都消失無蹤
And there won't be trace of anything we make now
所以你身在何方？ 能把你怎樣
So where are we? what fucked you?
我從不相信
I don't believe in one second that
數位影片或數位技術
digital imaging or digital technology
會改變人類說故事的方式
will ever take the way the humanity of story-telling
2001太空漫遊，1968
因為這關於我們的本質
beause story-telling in it on ourselves
這是神聖的人類事物
it's a holy human concern
藝術家忠於本質，科學家自然也是
artist primordial, science also quite primordial
這其實很和諧
so kind of all these things are very harmony things
他們總是在互相推進
They always had to push on one another
我們已經達到化學攝影技術的頂端
We are at the top of photo chemical process
也就能走這麼遠了
This is about far as we're ever gonna go
但是用數位技術的話，我們就重新回歸到初始了
When you are using digital, you are at the very bottom again
所以要跳出傳統幫助創新
So you should jump over and help to build that
因為越多人使用才能使這項技術更進一步
Cause more people use it, the better it gets
除非你參與到這場變革中
Unless you are participate into the revolution
否則就會被淘汰
Or you will be lost in past
我們不能說“沒我的事
We can't call ourselves as “we don't care
看你們了”
They are up to your guys now”
我們要參與其中
So we have to be in it
每個人都能參與到這個過程中
Everyone will have access to both the means of the production
也能立刻了解到曾經發生的事
and watch everything ever exist instantly
隨著數位技術持續改變我們說故事的本質
As digital continues to change the nature of story-telling
我們也在改變
We also continue to change
甚至這種改變我自己都不能理解
In ways that I could not even understand
不過所有的都在改變，這就成了一場巨大的變革
But all things do that and it becomes a giant revolution
人們喜歡好故事，好故事能帶他們去從未體驗過的世界
People love great stories, they let them getting into the world they haven't experienced
至於是怎麼樣的過程，我覺得並不重要
And how they get there, it doesn't really matter
我們開始使用數位技術到如今的程度，並不意味著停滯不前了
One shouldn't even think we stop when now we reach digital this is it
完全不是，想想看娛樂形式如何表現
No, no, think about where the entertainment imports
大眾需求又何去何從
Where the need is going to go
你認為你在技術上處於哪個層級？
Do you feel technologically with where you are
是否得心應手？
Dou you feel free
我不認為我想要去感覺
I'm not sure that I ever want to feel
我們已經到達了一定程度，從技術上講
that we arrived, technologically
我覺得我們總能做得更好
I always feel that there is something we can do better
我們的前輩給了世界一個夢想的新時代
The people who coming to us gave the world new ace to dream
我認為我們要繼續他們的使命
I think it's our job to continue that
繼續給人們創造夢想
and to try to give people new ace to dream
所有最後都會回歸到一件事
Everything comes down to one thing
如果你用心去做
If you do something with your heart
如果能夠讓我們產生共鳴
if you do something convince us to feel about it
那你拿什麼做到的並不重要
It doesn't matter what you using